<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Adam's Writing Thing</title><link>https://kalverra.github.io/</link><description>Adam's Writing Thing</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kalverra.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Do I Have ADHD?</title><link>https://kalverra.github.io/essays/do-i-have-adhd/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kalverra.github.io/essays/do-i-have-adhd/</guid><description>&lt;p>At this point, I’m pretty positive I do, but I’m still not fully convinced, and I’m still not entirely sure why I’m not entirely sure yet. Maybe this essay exists solely for my own benefit of organizing my thoughts and feelings on the matter, or maybe someone else will find this enlightening as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was recently diagnosed with ADHD by a psychiatrist and my primary care doctor who concurred. I’m 28 years old and was never flagged as ADHD before, but I suspect that is largely because I was in environments that were maybe not the best at recognizing or even acknowledging the existence of ADHD. Here are some myth-busting and baseline premises I’ve discovered as part of this process.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>ADHD is a real thing that affects how your brain works. It has been &lt;a href="https://www.additudemag.com/brain-mri-scans-adhd-research/">picked up in brain scans&lt;/a> (though &lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7879851/">it’s not fully settled on how that works yet&lt;/a>), and we can reliably diagnose it by looking at the repeated behaviors of those who have it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It is commonly diagnosed in children but can be discovered and diagnosed in adults. (There are some rumblings of &lt;a href="https://add.org/can-adhd-appear-for-the-first-time-in-adulthood/">adult-onset ADHD being a thing&lt;/a>, but most people think it’s adults that never got diagnosed.)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The concept of ADHD has been around since &lt;a href="https://www.notion.so/Therapy-and-ADHD-b0935a99286841ab8c0800ff234760bc?pvs=21">the early 1900s&lt;/a>. There are some theories that our current environment of overwhelming technology has contributed to its existence (I’m currently surrounded by four computer monitors and a cell phone, all buzzing notifications at me), but there’s no definitive word on that yet, and it’s certainly not the only cause.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.cdc.gov/ncbddd/adhd/data.html">About 13% of U.S. boys are diagnosed&lt;/a>, and 6% of girls. However, there is &lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8042533/">some agreement that we’ve been a bit too trigger-happy with that diagnosis&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It is genetic. If one of your parents has it, there’s a &lt;a href="https://www.notion.so/Therapy-and-ADHD-b0935a99286841ab8c0800ff234760bc?pvs=21">roughly 35% chance you do&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There are a few different treatment approaches, but behavioral interventions (&lt;a href="https://todoist.com/productivity-methods/pomodoro-technique">Pomodoro timers&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://todoist.com/productivity-methods/getting-things-done">GTD method&lt;/a>) + stimulant medications (Adderall, Vyvanse, etc) seem to be by far the most effective.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>“Adderall/Vyvanse/Whatever is just giving kids meth” is… well &lt;a href="https://www.astralcodexten.com/p/know-your-amphetamines">kind of true&lt;/a>. Though there’s a massive difference between taking a dose or two of highly controlled and regulated Adderall in the morning and shoving crystal meth up your butt for 3 days straight, they’re chemically very similar.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-it" >What Is It?
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#what-is-it">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>There are plenty of better resources on this; I particularly liked &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hFL6qRIJZ_Y">this Andrew Huberman podcast&lt;/a> on the matter (his &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2024/mar/28/podcaster-andrew-huberman-goop-for-bros">recent controversy&lt;/a> and weird following aside, the content seems solid).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I best understood it as a computer metaphor. A brain’s default process looks for information all around it, noticing everything it can. When it finds an idea or a sensation it wants to focus on, it quiets this primary process and gives way to a focused process that can shut out the noise around it and dive deep into that area for a limited amount of time. When that focus process is finished, or runs out of energy to continue, the primary process re-asserts itself and starts looking for something new to focus on. Occasionally there’s a bug or misunderstanding, and the primary and focus processes get out of sync. They both try to run at the same time or not at all. So while you’re trying to read a book or finish something at work, a million other things are going through your mind. Or your brain feels so blocked and empty that your only desire is to lay motionless in a dark room. This is an annoying occurrence for neurotypical people, but is a way of life for ADHD people. Also it’s suspected ADHD people have &lt;a href="https://www.thinkkids.com/blog/how-adhd-contributes-to-memory-problems">less RAM&lt;/a> than most others.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-do-i-think-i-have-it" >Why Do I Think I Have It?
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#why-do-i-think-i-have-it">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Mostly because multiple doctors, after listening to my issues and having me take &lt;a href="https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/adhd-questionnaire-ASRS111.pdf">this survey&lt;/a>, said I do. Also, the more I learn about &lt;a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/adult-adhd/symptoms-causes/syc-20350878">common symptoms&lt;/a> and listen to the stories of others with ADHD, all of these things match my experience to an uncanny degree. Some that match with me particularly:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Easily overwhelmed when faced with what most would consider a reasonable task list.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Extreme difficulty concentrating on any one thing, even things I enjoy like TV, books, and video games. It’s easy to feel restless and reach out for the next thing, and the internet is an especially dangerous tool to have here. I’ll start something at work I’m excited about, then some other random thought will enter my mind, and in no time, the day will be done. I’ll be watching two videos in the background about system design while reading some esoteric article on poisonous frogs. Even as I write this, I’ve switched my attention to a bunch of random, unconnected topics. I’ve also jumped around the essay itself, writing a couple sentences in one spot and then jumping halfway down the page to elaborate on some other point.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Except sometimes when my brain decides something is unbelievably fascinating, so much so that I’ll forget to shower or eat because I need to know every detail about how dogs’ noses work. Most people refer to this as &lt;a href="https://add.org/adhd-hyperfocus/">hyperfocus&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Hearing the phrase “wasted potential” a lot as a kid.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Constantly forgetting appointments, where I put my keys, how to get home, and the names of people I’ve known for weeks.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I can never seem to finish anything. My history is littered with assignments, hobbies, and projects that all are close to the finish line, but never made it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I have a hard time getting to sleep because I’m always thinking of &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/ADHD_Programmers/top/">random bullshit that I need to know about NOW&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I’m constantly fidgeting with something, getting up to pace, or generally being restless.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I have multiple relatives, including both my mother and grandmother, who have either official diagnoses or match a lot of the above symptoms.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I was recently prescribed Adderall, and it was such an emotional experience I cried with joy at the end of the day, a reaction that is nearly ubiquitous among ADHD people and not all that common among others.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>When listing these symptoms, it’s common for people to say things like, “I forget my keys and get distracted sometimes too. That doesn’t mean I’m ADHD,” to which you’d be right. Human brains are all broadly similar. We all get sad, distracted, and prideful sometimes. But there’s a difference between experiencing something occasionally and experiencing something almost always. Everyone gets sad, but not everyone is depressed. Everyone gets distracted, but not everyone has ADHD. Everyone has moments of pride, but not everyone is a narcissist. But when these things happen every day, so much so that your wife is frequently mad at you because of your inability to remember plans or appointments; or you need to designate a specific place in your house where your keys and wallet go, otherwise you will lose countless time every day looking for them, you’ve established a pattern of behavior that indicates your brain works differently than others.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-am-i-not-fully-convinced-i-do" >Why Am I Not Fully Convinced I Do?
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#why-am-i-not-fully-convinced-i-do">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>I still hold this doubt in the back of my mind, so I will lay down my primary reasons for doubting and then try to debunk them because I’m more willing to believe multiple medical professionals on this matter than my own, uneducated doubts.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="its-statistically-unlikely" >It’s Statistically Unlikely
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#its-statistically-unlikely">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>This is the easiest to knock down. Even if we over-diagnose ADHD in the U.S., it’s still not a tiny probability. The lowest estimate I could find for ADHD &lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7916320/">occurrence in my demographic was 6.76%&lt;/a>, which is a slightly higher chance than rolling a one on a d20 die. If you’ve played enough Dungeons and Dragons, you know from personal experience that those odds are small, but they’re sure as shit not impossible.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="i-dont-match-all-of-the-symptoms" >I Don’t Match All of the Symptoms
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#i-dont-match-all-of-the-symptoms">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>ADHD is most commonly diagnosed in elementary or middle school. The stereotypical ADHD kid is always hyper-energy, can never sit still, is always getting in trouble, and has abysmal grades. A lot of adult ADHD sufferers also deal with impulsiveness and its consequences, like terrible credit scores, gambling debt, or an inordinately high amount of jobs and relationships.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was never a troublemaker as a kid, and while my grades were never spectacular, I typically excelled in English and History while underperforming in almost everything else. No one ever flagged me as ADHD when I was a kid&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. As an adult, I’ve made a few impulsive decisions here and there, but am relatively boring.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is all true, but it ignores the fact that a diagnosis of something does not require the presence of every single symptom. I’ve undeniably had COVID-19 at least three times. I displayed a lot of symptoms, but I never felt one of the most common COVID symptoms: a shortage of breath. That doesn’t mean I never had COVID; I have multiple tests to disprove that assumption.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="i-could-be-fooling-myself" >I Could Be Fooling Myself
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#i-could-be-fooling-myself">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>There is a psychological phenomenon called the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barnum_effect">Forer Effect&lt;/a> that I’m afraid of falling into. It’s a tendency for people to interpret very general statements about the human experience as having deep personal insight into themselves. Statements like “You have a tendency to be critical of yourself” and “You have a great need for other people to like and admire you” are general enough they apply to everyone, but when you hear them it’s common to think it describes you in particular and feel a deep emotional reaction. It’s how psychics and mind readers &lt;a href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/1224176/psychic-services-market-size-us/">make so much money&lt;/a> tricking you into thinking they have a particularly deep insight into your pysche.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But ADHD symptoms don’t seem to have that quality. There are some that are pretty general like, “You often feel overwhelmed when a lot is expected of you at once”, but others that are much more specific like, “You find it incredibly difficult to finish a task, even if the hardest parts are already done” or “You often feel overly active and compelled to do things, like you were driven by a motor.”&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-is-it-a-problem" >Why Is It a Problem?
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#why-is-it-a-problem">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Alright, I have it. Why is it something worth fixing?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_dUNWW2D3BM">This Ken Robinson talk&lt;/a> about education and ADHD makes a good point about how we see ADHD as a problem not because our brains are built wrong, but because the education system is. Society has been designed in overt and subtle ways to move all of humanity into some narrow pathways, pathways that don’t play to the strengths of ADHD people. While I can’t reform society, I can try finding a different niche within it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The problem is that I’m already in a niche considered nearly optimal for ADHD people. Being a software developer plays to many of ADHD’s strengths, where we can bounce around the walls learning 15 different things a day and then spend a week holed up doing nothing but hyper-focusing on a program. But it’s still an issue for me. My focus is scattered and unpredictable. It’s preventing me from where I want to go in my life and career, and it’s been something both my teammates and I have been frustrated with.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It also makes me anxious and &lt;a href="./working-through-depression.md">depressed consistently&lt;/a>. I always end the day tired because I was “working” all day, but I get very little done. So I’m exhausted, disappointed with myself, depressed at how little progress I’m making, and anxious for the next day. It’s been an unpleasant way of existing, and I thought it was normal for so long. To find out that it’s not has been a revelation.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="how-do-i-fix-it" >How Do I Fix It?
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#how-do-i-fix-it">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>My main complaint is lack of focus, specifically lacking consistent and controlled focus. I’m blessed with a flexible schedule, but it’s not flexible enough to let me sit around all day and wait for inspiration. So I need to focus (hehe) on solving that aspect. Other parts of my ADHD have proven useful in my life and career, being able to swap between a ton of things with little friction has led me to some interesting learning experiences.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="the-usuals" >The Usuals
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#the-usuals">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>A good diet, consistent exercise, lots of sleep, and cutting out things like alcohol are table stakes when dealing with pretty much any human issue. No matter who you are, if you don’t have these things together, you’re sabotaging any other solutions you come up with.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="pharmaceuticals" >Pharmaceuticals
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#pharmaceuticals">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Aside from the basics, good old-fashioned American drugs are the most effective way to treat ADHD. In children, they can even help change the structure of your brain over time so that ADHD doesn’t really bother you in adulthood anymore, which is badass. But for those of us who missed that boat, drugs are pretty much unavoidable for the rest of our lives.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are some non-stimulant medications you can take to help improve ADHD symptoms. &lt;a href="https://www.additudemag.com/wellbutrin-for-adhd/">Wellbutrin&lt;/a> is a depression medication that’s handy for this. It can also help with anxiety and depression, which tend to come packaged with ADHD. It didn’t do much for me, though.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://www.cdc.gov/ncbddd/adhd/treatment.html">obvious gotos&lt;/a> after that are &lt;a href="https://www.astralcodexten.com/p/know-your-amphetamines">amphetamines like Adderall and Vyvanse&lt;/a>. There’s a litany of different kinds, but they all do the same thing. For me, my first time on Adderall was a revelation akin to taking LSD for the first time. For the first time in my life, my brain was quiet. I didn’t get distracted all day by random bullshit, and at the end of the day, I was pleased. I finished a task from start to end, multiple tasks even! A feat that on a typical day seems impossible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are some risks to &lt;a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/12/28/adderall-risks-much-more-than-you-wanted-to-know/">using Adderall&lt;/a>. Dependency is the one I’m most concerned with. I’m still confused about what “addiction” means in this context. From Scott Alexander:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The data on this are really poor because it’s hard to define addiction. If a prescription stimulant user uses their stimulants every day, and feels really good on them, and feels really upset if they can’t get them…well, that’s basically the expected outcome.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I’ve heard anecdotally about people who become so dependent on Adderall that they become depressed zombies for long periods when they lose access to it. Given that amphetamine shortages &lt;a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/health/health-news/adhd-drug-shortage-adderall-ritalin-focalin-vyvanse-rcna137356">aren’t exactly rare events&lt;/a>, this is a real issue to consider. However, these stories tend to involve individuals with severe cases of ADHD. Before Adderall, they had so many issues in their interpersonal and professional lives that the possibility of dependence is more than worth the risk. Others can function fine if they miss a dose and regularly skip doses on weekends and vacations. I’m still new to this game but have found this strategy to be the best approach for me so far.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure>
&lt;img src="https://kalverra.github.io/images/do-i-have-adhd/focus_hours.png" alt="My tracked focus hours at work. Guess what day I started taking Adderall">
&lt;figcaption>My tracked focus hours at work. Guess what day I started taking Adderall&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="behavioral-interventions" >Behavioral Interventions
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#behavioral-interventions">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>It’s important to note that drugs aren’t a panacea. They unlock your ability to concentrate, but if you let yourself you can easily lock into learning about freshwater sharks all day instead of that program you need to write. Thankfully I’ve been working on these for a while&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> and have a pretty good stable of mental and tech tools that work for me.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Using &lt;a href="https://todoist.com/">TODOist&lt;/a> to keep track of my work and personal life tasks. Its reminders and scheduling are crucial for me to be able to remember to do anything. It also lets me break down tasks into smaller bites to fight of the &lt;a href="https://www.adhdcentre.co.uk/strategies-to-reduce-adhd-overwhelm/">dreaded overwhelm&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Using &lt;a href="https://pomofocus.io/app">Pomofocus&lt;/a> for my Pomodoro timers.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Using &lt;a href="https://blocksite.co/">Blocksite&lt;/a> to stop myself from going into unproductive rabbit holes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Meditation and mindfulness are &lt;a href="https://www.additudemag.com/how-to-meditate-for-adhd-symptoms/">helpful for ADHD people&lt;/a>. It’s been very effective for me to recognize when my attention is drifting and guiding it back to the thing I need to focus on. It is also surprisingly difficult to do consistently, even for neurotypical people.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Aggressively silencing notifications. During a Pomodoro session, I’ll make sure to put my phone on DND and stash it somewhere I can’t see it. Then on Slack, I’ll set my status to “Focusing” and pause notifications.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/@HowtoADHD">How to ADHD YouTube channel&lt;/a> has a lot of strategies and tips for handling common ADHD hurdles, and it’s short-format, engaging videos that are ideal for, well, people with ADHD.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="supplements" >Supplements
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#supplements">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>These vary wildly in effectiveness and have all sorts of issues as they’re unregulated, and frequently a &lt;a href="https://www.fda.gov/consumers/health-fraud-scams/health-fraud-product-database">favorite of fraudsters&lt;/a> to separate fools and cash from each other. That said, there are some that have minor but demonstrated helpful effects:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8875377/">Caffeine&lt;/a> can almost function like a micro does of Adderall for some people.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6093191/">Creatine&lt;/a> can help working memory. I mostly take it for muscle growth, but it has some small benefits to cognitive tasks.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fish Oil, specifically &lt;a href="https://www.additudemag.com/adhd-omega-3-benefits/">Omega-3s&lt;/a>, is particularly beneficial. There are a lot of claims about its benefits for heart health, and can apparently help a lot in focus and hyperactivity.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.nccih.nih.gov/health/ashwagandha">Ashwagandha&lt;/a> is a bit niche but apparently effective at &lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3221068/">improving attention&lt;/a>. Though I personally haven’t seen much benefit.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6574559/">L-theanine&lt;/a> is usually combined with a stimulant like caffeine or Adderall to help attention. There’s some anecdotal evidence out there and a few studies with small sample sizes. I haven&amp;rsquo;t tried it myself, but it might be next on the list.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="what-i-take-away-from-writing-this" >What I Take Away from Writing This
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#what-i-take-away-from-writing-this">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Well, I have ADHD. I think I&amp;rsquo;m ready to accept that. This was informative mostly for my own psyche, but on the miniscule chance that someone actually finds this, perhaps it can help them figure it out like I did. If you&amp;rsquo;re in that position, I will say I wish I had tried the scarier sounding interventions like Adderall sooner. It was akin to wearing glasses for the first time, and not at all how I expected it to be. It&amp;rsquo;s also tempting to think that discovering and treating something like this will ultimately &amp;ldquo;fix&amp;rdquo; you. It won&amp;rsquo;t, but it will help a whole lot.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>This could easily be due to the environment I was in at the time. The intricacies of ADHD still weren’t well understood at the time, especially outside of medical professionals. I was also a part of a school that held ADHD diagnoses with some suspicion, and I got the general vibe that most people didn’t believe it was a real thing. I thought I was just lazy or stupid.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>Funnily enough, building these behavioral solutions contributed to my discovery process. I kept on looking for solutions to my issues with focus and feeling overwhelmed, and I kept getting results back from ADHD guides and gurus. Which always struck me as a good idea, “Oh, I bet ADHD people have &lt;strong>way&lt;/strong> worse issues with this. They probably know what works well!” Then it dawned on me that many of these experiences sound awfully familiar…&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Review: Going Infinite</title><link>https://kalverra.github.io/books/review-going-infinite/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kalverra.github.io/books/review-going-infinite/</guid><description>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m a huge &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Lewis">Michael Lewis&lt;/a> stan. I&amp;rsquo;ve loved every book of his I&amp;rsquo;ve read (and all the movies based on them), and frequently listen to &lt;a href="https://www.pushkin.fm/podcasts/against-the-rules">his podcast&lt;/a>. I also have worked as a software developer for a cryptocurrency project for almost three years. So when I saw these two interests of mine colliding in &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/156552773-going-infinite">Going Infinite&lt;/a>, I slammed that pre-order button hard and finished this book within a week, light speed for me these days. The book details the rise and collapse of Sam Bankman-Fried (SBF) and his crypto exchange, FTX. If you&amp;rsquo;re here, I&amp;rsquo;m assuming you have at least the basics of the story. So I want to focus less on the quality of the book (from a narrative standpoint, it&amp;rsquo;s pretty good, albeit not my favorite of Lewis&amp;rsquo;s), and more about the discussion it sparked.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sbf-is-human" >SBF is Human
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#sbf-is-human">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>There&amp;rsquo;s been a lot of criticism directed at Lewis for this book, primarily because he was at least partially sympathetic towards SBF, both as a person, and about SBF&amp;rsquo;s side of the story when it comes to the collapse. Mostly I&amp;rsquo;m seeing a lot of people that are upset that SBF was painted as an odd human being, rather than the caricature of a sociopathic fraudster that everyone has already determined SBF to be&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. I have a few problems with this:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>You&amp;rsquo;re misunderstanding the point of Michael Lewis, he&amp;rsquo;s not an investigative journalist or a judge searching for scandal, he&amp;rsquo;s a writer who has a knack for finding interesting, complexly human characters amidst unusual circumstances.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I don&amp;rsquo;t think it&amp;rsquo;s particularly flattering towards SBF at all.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The book doesn&amp;rsquo;t attempt to absolve him of anything the U.S. government has accused him of.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>There&amp;rsquo;s been accusations that Sam put Lewis under his spell, and uses that visionary-jedi-mind-trick shit that &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_Holmes">Elizabeth Holmes&lt;/a> was &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jonwu_/status/1433595857304055814">still pulling off&lt;/a> even after Theranos went kaput. Or even that Lewis was wowed into loving SBF after being brought to ritzy parties with Leonardo DiCaprio and Hillary Clinton&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. Or even more ridiculously, that Lewis was bribed by SBF to portray him positively&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. I think Lewis was certainly fascinated by Sam, and tried to paint him as a human being (as much as he can resemble one) with plenty of flaws, and also as someone who would most definitely risk a bunch of money that he should not have been risking.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sbf-is-compelling" >SBF Is Compelling
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#sbf-is-compelling">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Lewis spends a lot of time on SBF&amp;rsquo;s positive qualities. He paints SBF as interesting and intelligent, a curious case of someone with almost negative charisma that turns it around into dazzling sophisticated investors and media types with his brilliance and quirkiness. This is a perfect character for Lewis, but I&amp;rsquo;ve heard a lot of people claim that mentioning these parts of SBF at all is proof that Lewis sees SBF as innocent or an overall good person. Or that Lewis is lying about these traits purely to puff up SBF. This is part of what I&amp;rsquo;m talking about that people have created a caricature of pure evil and negativity that SBF must match, or else Lewis is a fraud. If SBF wasn&amp;rsquo;t smart and compelling, none of us would be here. The same way Jobs bedazzled audiences with his vision and intelligence while being a raging asshole behind closed doors, SBF was an interesting person who managed to charm plenty of people, who also happened to have massive character flaws. Calling SBF intelligent, a good trader, or an interesting person to talk to doesn&amp;rsquo;t deny that he can also be a manipulative, irresponsible, prick. If he were just the last 3 things, I don&amp;rsquo;t think he would have gotten as far as he did, and Lewis would never have written about him.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sbf-is-a-dick" >SBF is a Dick
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#sbf-is-a-dick">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>SBF exhibits great qualities for a Wall Street trader; if given a good enough argument, he&amp;rsquo;ll unwaveringly commit, even if he personally has reservations. He ignores any personal hangups or emotions and follows whatever will most probably produce his desired outcome. And that desired outcome is not always bad, but he&amp;rsquo;s very ends-justify-the-means coded. He has no problem disregarding others&amp;rsquo; emotions and desires in pursuit of his own. Through how SBF treats his friends (exploiting their talents until they are no longer of use), his employees (making huge demands and failing to manage, empathize, or generally give a shit about their problems), and his girlfriend (emotionally neglecting her until he wants sex from her, then love-bombing until he gets what he wants and leaves), Lewis shows incontrovertibly that SBF is an emotionally manipulative asshole.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As far as SBF is concerned, books are stupid, boring, long, and should be shortened to a blog post. Adults are stupid too, anyone over the age of 30 has nothing useful left to say or do in their life (I wonder how this became a self-fulfilling prophecy given SBF&amp;rsquo;s conviction at the ripe age of 31). In fact, most everyone in the world is stupid besides SBF, because according to himself, SBF is a being of pure logic and thought rather than all those messy emotions that cloud judgement. Except for all those times that Lewis mentions his actions were clearly influenced by irrational emotion and lust, like when he moved the entire headquarters of FTX twice because of where his on-and-off girlfriend was located. Lewis showcases uncountable red flags in SBF&amp;rsquo;s personality, and while there is some acknowledgement of his better qualities, I don&amp;rsquo;t see how anyone could see this book as complimentary of Sam the person.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sbf-would-totally-do-illegal-shit" >SBF Would Totally Do Illegal Shit
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#sbf-would-totally-do-illegal-shit">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>He&amp;rsquo;s a gambler that has had reckless and illegal bets pay off before. It&amp;rsquo;s very clear that if he can make a bet he thinks he&amp;rsquo;ll win, he&amp;rsquo;ll take it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Alright, I&amp;rsquo;ve talked about how I think the book was good and painted SBF as a human, albeit not a sympathetic one. Now for the issues I have with it, which have grown in severity as I&amp;rsquo;ve written this.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="its-weird-lewis-didnt-mention-the-things" >It&amp;rsquo;s Weird Lewis Didn&amp;rsquo;t Mention The Thing(s)
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#its-weird-lewis-didnt-mention-the-things">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Lewis has mentioned that he left certain things out of the book because he felt it didn&amp;rsquo;t fit the story. This isn&amp;rsquo;t as sinister as it usually sounds (remember point 1 at the beginning of this), but it does remind us that he&amp;rsquo;s looking for an interesting tale, not so much an exhaustive expose to be read aloud in a court room. Even so, there are some bits that I think are pretty relevant to the story, and at the least it&amp;rsquo;s odd that Lewis doesn&amp;rsquo;t include them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Molly White &lt;a href="https://newsletter.mollywhite.net/p/review-michael-lewiss-going-infinite">goes over these omissions&lt;/a> in more detail; basically Lewis would mention something SBF did or said, but Lewis neglected to explicitly call out that the thing he did or said was immoral, illegal, or a lie. I&amp;rsquo;d be more willing to brush these omissions aside with the idea that Lewis wants to only tell the event how they happened, and not pass judgement. But in his other books, &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/26889576">The Big Short&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/46266188">The Fifth Risk&lt;/a>, and &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/56790170-the-premonition">The Premonition&lt;/a> Lewis has no problem calling organizations and individuals out as corrupt, incompetent, or evil. So while he never defends SBF&amp;rsquo;s actions&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>, he never admonishes them either. And that leaves a bad taste in my mouth now that I compare how he handled figures like Trump in his previous books.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Also, you&amp;rsquo;ve got to talk about when &lt;a href="https://www.vox.com/future-perfect/23462333/sam-bankman-fried-ftx-cryptocurrency-effective-altruism-crypto-bahamas-philanthropy">Sam Bankman-Fried tries to explain himself&lt;/a>. It&amp;rsquo;s a conversation SBF has with a reporter soon after the walls start to tumble down where he disavows his image as an effective altruist, claiming it was all just a PR stunt. In fact, all of his talks of ethics and altruism was a front for his true 4D chess match of minimizing risk to his reputation while maximizing returns to his bank account. I think this is a crucial part of SBF&amp;rsquo;s story, and for Lewis to not even mention it (the book was being written while this came out) still baffles me. Lewis&amp;rsquo; ongoing argument through the book is that SBF was nothing if not dedicated to his ideals, and while the ideals were admirable, Lewis paints SBF as a person who would do immoral, illegal, and emotionally abusive things on the road to those goals. Lewis definitely should have called out when SBF realized his goose was cooked, that he said, &amp;ldquo;nah, jk&amp;rdquo; to what those goals even were. Maybe Lewis didn&amp;rsquo;t want to include anything other than his own experience in the book? But come on man, give it a footnote at least.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="behind-the-bastards" >Behind the Bastards
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#behind-the-bastards">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m a fan of another podcast, &lt;a href="https://www.iheart.com/podcast/105-behind-the-bastards-29236323/">Behind the Bastards&lt;/a>, a wonderfully researched and funny exploration into some of history&amp;rsquo;s worst people (plus some less worse ones). They did a &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/lSbMy6vblsY?si=Srrqx-JfkaBDjbGK">short series on SBF&lt;/a> when he was under investigation, and then &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/a9tDihgEn2k?si=qBHkpFkydgIIyhbw">posted updates&lt;/a> shortly after his conviction. That 2 episode update was primarily a Michael Lewis beat down. I won&amp;rsquo;t go over all of it here, but it had some convincing arguments and information that helped sway me towards the side of Lewis being more wrong than right in his book. While it also contains some fallacies that I argue against at the beginning of this review, I found it to largely be the best critical-of-Lewis side of this argument I&amp;rsquo;ve seen.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="effective-altruism" >Effective Altruism
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#effective-altruism">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Scott Alexander&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://www.astralcodexten.com/p/in-continued-defense-of-effective">defense of effective altruism&lt;/a> is a worthy read in the face of all this. Much like Lewis&amp;rsquo; praise of SBF&amp;rsquo;s intelligence doesn&amp;rsquo;t make Lewis a fraud, SBF&amp;rsquo;s fall does not make effective altruism a fraud. I think it&amp;rsquo;s a movement that has caught a lot of undeserved stray shots in these SBF headlines. People donating their money for effective good in the world is always a win in my book, assuming they&amp;rsquo;re balancing their motives and bets.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>This seems to be running in tandem with &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/122765395-elon-musk">Walter Issacson&amp;rsquo;s biography on Elon Musk&lt;/a> which I haven&amp;rsquo;t read (yet), but have seen a lot of similar criticisms for. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t paint Musk to be an evil caricature, so that must confirm that Issacson is a Musk simp who was bribed into writing a book that does have plenty of criticism, but not an outright condemnation that people wanted.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve seen this particular accusation a few times, and always scratch my head. Lewis isn&amp;rsquo;t Brad Pitt or anything, but he&amp;rsquo;s decently famous and wealthy. Also, Brad Pitt is in 2 of the movies based on his books. He&amp;rsquo;s no famous billionaire, but it&amp;rsquo;s not as if Lewis is some shmuck who melts in the face of celebrity.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3">
&lt;p>This is an especially ludicrous and weirdly pervasive argument. See my above footnote; Lewis isn&amp;rsquo;t a billionaire, but he&amp;rsquo;s one of the most successful writers in the world who sold the movie rights to this book before it was even finished. Not only that, his family is old money rich, he&amp;rsquo;s got plenty of money. And even if SBF bribed him, with what? Lewis had front row seats to watch the money pile burn, he knows he&amp;rsquo;s not getting shit. And even if SBF had already paid, how would he hold Lewis accountable at this point?&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4">
&lt;p>Later on in his podcast about the book, he is quick to call out that SBF definitely did several illegal things, though I don&amp;rsquo;t think he mentions anything like that in the book.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Review: The Power of Habit</title><link>https://kalverra.github.io/books/review-the-power-of-habit/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kalverra.github.io/books/review-the-power-of-habit/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/12609433">The Power of Habit by Charles Duhigg&lt;/a> is the reason that I just turned on a &lt;a href="https://pomofocus.io/">Pomodoro timer&lt;/a> to write this review. He doesn&amp;rsquo;t ever mention it in his book (I think I &lt;a href="https://www.verywellmind.com/what-is-the-mandela-effect-4589394">Mandela effect&lt;/a>-ed myself into believing that was the case), I&amp;rsquo;d heard of a Pomodoro timer before, but largely dismissed it as being silly. This book takes you on a journey through the power of human habit that is so illuminating and powerful that it convinced me to take on new strategies to combat my worst habit: distractibility. So sit down and shut up reader, because for the remaining ~18 minutes&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>, I&amp;rsquo;m going to be so fucking focused on reviewing this book you&amp;rsquo;re not going to believe it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Duhigg starts small in scope, showing us the habits of individual smokers, over-eaters, alcoholics who are now regularly jogging, eating salads, and excelling in their careers. The first three &lt;em>before&lt;/em> descriptions don&amp;rsquo;t quite match with the &lt;em>after&lt;/em> ones, and that&amp;rsquo;s part of the point. One of the first revelations in the book is that &lt;strong>changing&lt;/strong> one bad habit often cascades into other parts of your life. Duhigg first focuses on Lisa, a smoker who was suffering through a rough divorce, and makes a rash trip to Cairo, even more rashly vowing that she would return in a year to trek through an Egyptian desert. For that to be possible, she decided she would need to give up smoking.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>[&amp;hellip;] to the scientists at the laboratory, the details of her trek weren&amp;rsquo;t relevant. Because for reasons they were just beginning to understand, that one small shift in Lisa&amp;rsquo;s perception that day in Cairo—the conviction that she &lt;em>had&lt;/em> to give up smoking to accomplish her goal—had touched off a series of changes that would ultimately radiate out to every part of her life. Over the next six months, she would replace smoking with jogging, and that, in turn, changed how she ate, worked, slept, saved money, scheduled her workdays, planned for the future, and so on. [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It wasn&amp;rsquo;t the trip to Cairo that had caused the shift, scientists were convinced, or the divorce or desert trek. It was that Lisa had focused on changing just one habit—smoking—at first. [&amp;hellip;] By focusing on one pattern—what is known as a &amp;ldquo;keystone habit&amp;rdquo;—Lisa had taught herself how to reprogram the other routines in her life, as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Keystone habits pop up a lot in this book, I&amp;rsquo;d call them, and &amp;ldquo;The Habit Loop&amp;rdquo;, the main characters, and probably what you should focus on if you&amp;rsquo;re hoping to use this book to change your own habits&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;img src="https://kalverra.github.io/images/review-the-power-of-habit/the-habit-loop.png" alt="the habit loop">
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Duhigg quickly establishes this loop and its power through a few studies (including the curious case of &lt;a href="https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2013/04/130422154947.htm">Eugene Pauly&lt;/a>, who suffered severe brain damage, leaving only his habitual mind) and applies it to each story in the book. The book is mostly stories and anecdotes from the subjects of these academic studies on habits. The structure is nicely done to stop the book from being too dry, using individual stories is effective for keeping my attention and getting your point across in concrete ways. But you can quit it with the bullshit cliffhangers all over the place. At least once a chapter Duhigg builds the story up to a point of &amp;ldquo;and you&amp;rsquo;ll never guess what happens next&amp;rdquo; then do a line break and jump back in the storyline, or sometimes to a totally different one. It&amp;rsquo;s not a large complaint, but it baffled me every time that this man is telling me to tune in next week so I can catch the thrilling conclusion to how Starbucks works.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The book is split into 3 parts, growing in scope as Duhigg explores habits in individuals, companies, and finally societies. This is where the more &amp;ldquo;academic&amp;rdquo; aspects of the book come in, and where I think it gets its most interesting, but also less useful for a distracted engineer to immediately incorporate in his life.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="part-1-habits-of-individuals" >Part 1: Habits of Individuals
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#part-1-habits-of-individuals">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Habits are hard to manufacture, that&amp;rsquo;s basically the entirety of LA Fitness&amp;rsquo;s business model. Get you to buy a membership intending to build this new, healthy habit, then make it impossible to cancel the thing when you inevitably don&amp;rsquo;t actually go with a combination of shame and bureaucratic bullshittery. It&amp;rsquo;s tricky because habits are built in pursuit of a reward, and if you don&amp;rsquo;t find an obvious reward at the end of that treadmill, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to keep up, and if for whatever reason your brain isn&amp;rsquo;t coded to accept that exercise endorphin rush as a good thing, then you&amp;rsquo;ve got to employ other strategies. For this reason only one chapter is spent on creating new habits, while most others are focused on changing existing ones.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Habits aren&amp;rsquo;t destiny. [&amp;hellip;] habits can be ignored, changed, or replaced. But the reason the discovery of the habit loop is so important is that it reveals a basic truth: When a habit emerges, the brain stops fully participating in decision making. It stops working so hard, or diverts focus to other tasks. So unless you deliberately &lt;em>fight&lt;/em> a habit—unless you find new routines—the pattern will unfold automatically.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, simply understanding how habits work—learning the structure of the habit loop—makes them easier to control. Once you break a habit into its components, you can fiddle with the gears.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The power of habit is that our brains run a program in the background to save its energy when certain conditions are met. And if you can modify the program, you can train your brain in some useful ways. As a programmer this is a fascinating revelation, that my brain is running &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cron">cron jobs&lt;/a> all the time, and with a little work I can tweak the commands being run. But I can never delete them. This seems accepted a priori in the book, that habits are near impossible to fully delete. Duhigg writes, if you&amp;rsquo;ve &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_Pavlov">Pavlov&lt;/a>-ed&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> yourself into drinking a beer every time the football game is on, you&amp;rsquo;ll find it incredibly difficult to stop and just drink nothing. Your cue (football game), routine (get a beer), and reward (taste and sweet oblivion) have been indelibly established. You&amp;rsquo;ll have much better luck tweaking the routine part&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> of that habit loop, so reaching for a seltzer water or non-alcoholic beer instead will greatly increase your chances of changing your routine. The difficult part here is stopping your brain from shutting off. You have to be vigilant to recognize the habit and each part of the loop that is in play. When you&amp;rsquo;ve done that, you then have to stop your brain from going with its usual behavior and shift it to the new one.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I get the sense that Duhigg isn&amp;rsquo;t a big drinker, smoker, or recreational drug user of any kind. The book has little lip service paid to the unending difficulties of uprooting bad habits like addictive drugs, lip service that most current and former drug aficionados cannot resist opining on. Although he brings up examples of people quitting smoking and drinking utilizing these habit-modification techniques (there&amp;rsquo;s quite a few mentions of Alcoholics Anonymous), there&amp;rsquo;s little said about chemical addiction. It seems to me that chemical addiction would be something like habit formation in overdrive, or it maybe reinforces the reward part of the loop so deeply that nothing else can emulate it. Though he does acknowledge this is all easier said than done.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>It is important to note that though the process of habit change is easily described, it does not necessarily follow that it is easily accomplished. It is facile to imply that smoking, alcoholism, overeating, or other ingrained patterns can be upended without real effort. Genuine change requires work and self-understanding of the cravings driving behaviors. Changing any habit requires determination. No one will quit smoking cigarettes simply because they sketch a habit loop.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="part-2-habits-of-companies" >Part 2: Habits of Companies
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#part-2-habits-of-companies">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Keystone habits pop up occasionally when Duhigg talks about individuals, but they really come into play for corporate habits. I think because a corporation is a much bigger beast than an individual, so if you&amp;rsquo;re looking to change any habits, there&amp;rsquo;s mountains more friction in your way, so picking a single habit that can have far-reaching consequences if far preferable. He opens this section by exploring the newly appointed CEO of the Aluminum Company of America (Alcoa), Paul O&amp;rsquo;Neill. O&amp;rsquo;Neill sought to turn around the flailing company by doing something no 1980s business man could dream of: make the workplace safer.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>O&amp;rsquo;Neill believed that some habits have the power to start a chain reaction, changing other habits as they move through an organization. Some habits, in other words, matter more than others in remaking businesses and lives. These are &amp;ldquo;keystone habits,&amp;rdquo; and they can influence how people work, eat, play, live, spend, and communicate. Keystone habits start a process that, over time, transforms everything.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>O&amp;rsquo;Neill identified factory safety as the keystone habit to change, and he really fucking cared about it. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t some bullshit pandering that bigwigs said to quiet the rabble, he bought better machines, implemented new standards, and fired an effective executive when that exec was slow to report an incident in accordance with O&amp;rsquo;Neill&amp;rsquo;s new standards. Before O&amp;rsquo;Neill, the company was getting wrecked by competitors, and everyone assumed this focus on safety would slow down Alcoa even more. His investors balked in classic 1980s businessman fashion: &amp;ldquo;Profit is driven by children&amp;rsquo;s faces covered in coal dust! Asbestos filled machines with every surface sharpened to a razor&amp;rsquo;s edge! If I so much as hear about an emergency shutoff I&amp;rsquo;m going to fill the room with chainsaws!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But O&amp;rsquo;Neill kept at it, the safety records meaningfully improved, as did the rest of the company. It turns out safety was a keystone habit and improving it triggered a slew of other improvements. The newer machines were safer, they also jammed less and made better products. Workers trusted management more, management trusted workers more, and overall productivity soared.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>If you focus on changing or cultivating keystone habits, you can cause widespread shifts. However, identifying keystone habits is tricky. To find them, you have to know where to look. Detecting keystone habits means searching out certain characteristics. Keystone habits offer what is known within academic literature as &amp;ldquo;small wins.&amp;rdquo; They help other habits to flourish by creating new structures, and they establish cultures where change becomes contagious.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The &amp;ldquo;if you know where to look&amp;rdquo; part is the rub here, as not much direction is given in that aspect. Though just observationally through some of the book&amp;rsquo;s examples, the answer tends to be something innocuous that also touches many aspects of the whole process&lt;sup id="fnref:5">&lt;a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. If you can change that, so much more can change as well. For individuals, a common one is exercise, but I&amp;rsquo;m unsure if companies share any common ones to focus on.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The other big example Duhigg uses isn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily the habit of a company, but rather how companies have independently discovered the powers of habit, and effectively exploit them to a creepy degree. He details the story of Target&amp;rsquo;s data scientists who were able to spot when people were pregnant, sometimes even before the mothers themselves knew. Target would track purchase histories, and found out that newly-pregnant women bought at each stage of pregnancy, and would send them coupons for those items. New mothers found this creepy as shit&lt;sup id="fnref:6">&lt;a href="#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">6&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>, so Target learned to get sneaky with it. You&amp;rsquo;d get a coupon booklet for a bunch of stuff, plus a couple of totally-not-targeted stroller and diaper discounts.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="part-3-habits-of-societies" >Part 3: Habits of Societies
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#part-3-habits-of-societies">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>This section has me conflicted. I simultaneously believe Duhigg is reaching too far, but maybe has a point. The big focus is the &lt;a href="https://kinginstitute.stanford.edu/montgomery-bus-boycott">Montgomery bus boycott&lt;/a> that Rosa Parks kicked off, and launched MLK. Duhigg&amp;rsquo;s argument is that anti-black discrimination in Montgomery was habitual. The exchange between Rosa Parks and the cop who arrested her bolsters this (and is also pretty gangster shit from Rosa Parks).&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;If you don&amp;rsquo;t stand up,&amp;rdquo; [the bus driver] said, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m going to call the police and have you arrested.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;You may do that,&amp;rdquo; Parks said.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The driver left and found two policemen.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Why don&amp;rsquo;t you stand up?&amp;rdquo; one of them asked Parks after they boarded.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Why do you push us around?&amp;rdquo; she said&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know,&amp;rdquo; the officer answered. &amp;ldquo;But the law is the law and you&amp;rsquo;re under arrest.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;You may do that&amp;rdquo; is a fantastic, movie-worthy line, and so is the officer saying &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know&amp;rdquo;. It perfectly encapsulates Duhigg&amp;rsquo;s point that this discrimination had fallen into the habit loop where white people didn&amp;rsquo;t even think about their behavior, their brains went on auto-pilot and discriminated because it was the easy thing to do, and black people withstood the abuse because they had adopted a habit to do so.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A lot has been said about why specifically Parks was the one to spark this revolution, she wasn&amp;rsquo;t the first black person to refuse to give up her seat on the bus, but she was a beloved community figure who was involved with a lot of tight-knit communities in the area, so she was easy to rally around. There were a lot of social science phenomena going on during the Montgomery bus boycotts, but I&amp;rsquo;m not fully convinced that habits were a part of it. Duhigg asserts that habits of friendship and social interaction dictate a lot of what happened in Montgomery.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Movements don&amp;rsquo;t emerge because everyone suddenly decides to face the same direction at once. They rely on social patterns that begin as the habits of friendship, grow through the habits of communities, and are sustained by new habits that change participants&amp;rsquo; sense of self.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I still think Duhigg is doing some round-peg-square-hole work here. Habits are powerful forces in our lives, as he&amp;rsquo;s proved in previous chapters, but was it adherence to habits that kept protestors in the streets? Or was it the power of the ideals they were fighting for, and the extraordinarily charismatic leader in MLK that kept them going? I&amp;rsquo;d wager the latter as a more powerful force in compelling behavior on this sort of scale.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-freewill-thing" >The Freewill Thing
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#the-freewill-thing">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Habits are a powerful and fundamental force of the human mind. We quite literally stop thinking and assessing our actions for moments of time to get our reward. So are we a slave to the habits? Are we simply collections of cron jobs running all day? And are we responsible for their consequences?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So much of my own time has been spent on pushing this freewill thought around in circles I kind of checked out for this section. I think freewill is the ultimate &lt;a href="https://xkcd.com/356/">nerd-snipe&lt;/a> for the philosophically minded, and until we can get some sort of smoking gun, we&amp;rsquo;re going nowhere. And habits are not that smoking gun. Duhigg clearly shows that with a little work, we can modify and interrupt habits. Maybe you lose autonomy for a little bit, but you can recognize and fight it with the proper willpower, strategy, and assistance.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="key-takeaways" >Key Takeaways
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#key-takeaways">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The habit loop is powerful, and shuts your brain off to save energy. Knowing this enables you to recognize the loop and modify it, which is generally the best way to approach things as habits are hard to manufacture, but relatively easy to change.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Habits are near impossible to completely delete without some surgery or copious amounts of booze.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Recognizing the habit is the first step, then the hard work of actually changing it begins.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>How to Modify the Habit&lt;/strong>: nail down the loop and you can change it. The loop components can be hard to spot.
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Identify the routine: figure out what habits you have&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Experiment with rewards: figure out what exactly the reward is, try new ones, see if you&amp;rsquo;re satisfied&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Isolate the cue: we&amp;rsquo;re bombarded with info and events, you need the exact thing that triggers your habit&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Have a plan: devise a specific plan that modifies the habit and execute it dutifully&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>This took far more time and timer session to finish than I anticipated. I had a draft where I included whenever I finished a session, but discarded that bit as it added little more than clutter. Albeit it&amp;rsquo;s an effective tool, enough that I already resisted trying to build my own program to do it, and bought my lifetime subscription to &lt;a href="https://pomofocus.io/app">Pomofocus&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>As I imagine 99% of people who read this book are.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3">
&lt;p>Pavlov is not mentioned in this book at all. Not a single reference. I figure his work is probably wildly out of date at this point, and I can imagine anyone &lt;a href="https://www.iflscience.com/pavlov-s-dog-experiment-was-much-more-disturbing-than-you-think-65729">who loves dogs would probably not want to acknowledge his existence&lt;/a>, but still, seems like an odd exclusion.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4">
&lt;p>I guess you could also eliminate the cue in this case, just never watch football. But that&amp;rsquo;s probably a non-starter for most.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:5">
&lt;p>Side rant: I think focusing on eliminating automated test flakes would be a great candidate for this in a software company. Flakes are often frustrating, but accepted matter-of-fact and people just re-run the test. I think prioritizing eliminating flakey tests can bring a massive amount of organizational focus to bear on overall product quality. Less bugs and crashes, more focus on building maintainable and testable code, and less likelihood to ship broken shit.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:6">
&lt;p>This is maybe showing the age of the book, but this felt very much like Duhigg was trying to shock me with the revelation that &amp;ldquo;corporations track your behavior!&amp;rdquo;, and I could feel his mood fall as I told him &amp;ldquo;ya, no shit they do&amp;rdquo;. I was also hoping for more deep dive on exactly the math/programming that went into Target&amp;rsquo;s system at the time, but I left understandably disappointed.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Working Through Depression</title><link>https://kalverra.github.io/essays/working-through-depression/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kalverra.github.io/essays/working-through-depression/</guid><description>&lt;p>My brain broke again and I&amp;rsquo;m sad all the time. Depression and anxiety aren&amp;rsquo;t foreign concepts to me; before I ever identified them using those words, the feelings have burst over me ever since I was in Elementary school. With no discernable origin&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>, feelings of hopelessness and worthlessness accost my brain and leave it in some mental ditch. I can&amp;rsquo;t do much of anything without finding some sort of flaw in my actions, methodology, motivations, and execution. Anything I do or produce is bad and I should feel bad about it. This of course spirals to making me feel bad that I&amp;rsquo;m beating myself up this way, and gives me zero leeway to feel pride or accomplishment in anything I do&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;img src="https://kalverra.github.io/images/working-through-depression/feel_bad.png" alt="Zoidberg echoing my flawless logic">
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>How you get there and what it looks like is different for everyone, but the basic chemical feedback loop of hopelessness and worthlessness and not bothering trying things or enjoying things because what&amp;rsquo;s the point anyway, tends to be the same. This is of course infuriating because actively doing and enjoying things is pretty much the only way to work your way out of a depressive episode. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to feel hopeless and worthless when all you do is lay in bed all day doing nothing, so you just reinforce your &lt;a href="https://www.health.harvard.edu/blog/how-to-recognize-and-tame-your-cognitive-distortions-202205042738">cognitive distortions&lt;/a> and end up transforming them from distortions into realities.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Working past depression is hard, monotonous work. Convincing myself that I&amp;rsquo;m worthy of treatment in the first place is tricky&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. Therapy, medication, exercise, and celebrating my accomplishments all mean taking some amount of initiative to schedule an appointment, or drive to a gym, or do something in the first place, which to a person who views getting out from under the covers as an insurmountable challenge, these all are ludicrously difficult, not to mention what would be the point anyway? I can&amp;rsquo;t willpower depression away the same way I can&amp;rsquo;t just sheer effort myself better from the flu. But I can willpower myself towards the things that can help me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is where the title&amp;rsquo;s double-meaning kicks in: I still gotta work. Beating myself up while laying still in bed isn&amp;rsquo;t an option, I have to take the show on the road. Both to try and fix the issue, and to avoid even more issues. I&amp;rsquo;ve succumbed to the temptation to just bury my head in a pillow and eschew all responsibilities before, and the consequences can be immense. I nearly failed a couple classes in high school, which at the time felt like the end of the world&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>, but now I&amp;rsquo;m an honest-to-goodness adult, I have so many more opportunities to fuck up my life! I could lose my job, ruin relationships and opportunities while laying motionless, wondering what the point of it all is. So I&amp;rsquo;m still working, I&amp;rsquo;m still going to the gym, walking the dog, keeping the house clean, and trying to celebrate even the smallest of accomplishments. I just do it all through a haze, like I&amp;rsquo;m in some old allergy medicine commercial, walking through a beautiful field of flowers while frowning underneath a grey filter. Even now writing these words I&amp;rsquo;m frustrated at how cliche I sound, what a horrible writer I am, how no one will ever read this&lt;sup id="fnref:5">&lt;a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> and I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t even bother. But I&amp;rsquo;m gonna fucking write it and post it through sheer determination that I can pat myself on the back that I actually finished something, even if I think it&amp;rsquo;s trite garbage. And I&amp;rsquo;ll do it tomorrow, committing some code I think is bad, and it may or may not actually be bad, but I won&amp;rsquo;t ever admit I think it&amp;rsquo;s good because I made it, making it naturally inferior. But I committed it, so I at least got that far.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This process is exhausting from a willpower standpoint, so you have to be smart about where to invest it. I&amp;rsquo;m getting my work done, but the bed if often unmade, the laundry piles up, and I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten trigger-happy with ordering takeout for dinner. It&amp;rsquo;s also exhausting from the pure banality of the process. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to get lost in the monotony of life on a good day, but when your brain has decided that it&amp;rsquo;s all going to be boring and unsatisfying no matter what, it&amp;rsquo;s suffocating. It&amp;rsquo;s made even worse knowing that there is no real end-game here. My prize is that I keep on living life, but with more flavor. I don&amp;rsquo;t reach some magical epiphany and ascend into Nirvana, I don&amp;rsquo;t even find an excitingly new answer. I know the answer, I beat myself up too much. I need to be kinder to myself. But telling me that is as good as telling someone with an eating disorder that they need to just eat differently. Or telling an alcoholic that alcohol is unhealthy. No shit. But you have to keep reminding yourself every minute of that same, uninspiring and uncomplicated answer to make any progress. And it never stops being annoying. The road to recovery is paved with tired platitudes, and sports a million billboards of infuriatingly obvious motivational posters.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>This is an annoying wrinkle to the whole ordeal. There&amp;rsquo;s rarely a definitive cause to these feelings. While a tragic event, or other life stressors certainly can kick off the chemical cascade, for me it&amp;rsquo;s rarely the case. The feelings pummel me at random. I often wish I could identify some definitive cause, as if I could shout &amp;ldquo;Eureka!&amp;rdquo; at it and have all my emotional issues immediately solved, &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/ZQht2yOX9Js?si=5cXyfCkKqoU7wnp0">Good Will Hunting style&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>An example of such thinking recently when writing some code: &amp;ldquo;This code is garbage, why can&amp;rsquo;t I write anything good? Will anyone actually use this or care? I hope not, if anyone sees this they&amp;rsquo;ll realize how bad I am at programming. Oh look, a bug, I should have thought of that before. I&amp;rsquo;m so stupid. Why am I being so hard on myself? I need to stop doing that, I&amp;rsquo;m my own worst enemy, it&amp;rsquo;s why I&amp;rsquo;ll never succeed in life. My boss said I&amp;rsquo;m doing well, but he&amp;rsquo;s just lying and trying to be nice, just like my wife when she said I&amp;rsquo;m doing a good job&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; and so on, in perpetuity, etcetera.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3">
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m constantly working past the fact that I&amp;rsquo;m a college educated white dude in the U.S. with a white collar job that I really enjoy. I feel like I don&amp;rsquo;t deserve to be depressed, or don&amp;rsquo;t deserve treatment, I already hit so many damn lotteries! This reeks of the same logic as &amp;ldquo;there are starving children in Africa, so you need to finish all your food&amp;rdquo;. No matter what I do with the food on my plate, I ain&amp;rsquo;t solving the more tragic problem. So I need to just eat/not-eat/whatever the fuck is the option that makes sense in this simile.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4">
&lt;p>This eventually led me to get rejected from most colleges I applied to, which again felt like the apocalypse. Ultimately I think this actually worked out for the best, but good luck trying to convince me of that at the time.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:5">
&lt;p>And even if they did, they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t enjoy it or connect with it.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Review: A Philosophy of Software Design</title><link>https://kalverra.github.io/books/review-a-philosophy-of-software-design/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kalverra.github.io/books/review-a-philosophy-of-software-design/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/39996759">A Philosophy of Software Design by John Ousterhout&lt;/a> is a wide ranging, highly opinionated look at general software design practices and how to best implement them. It vacillates from big-picture musings on &amp;ldquo;The Nature of Complexity&amp;rdquo;, down to seemingly miniscule squabbles around &amp;ldquo;Choosing Names&amp;rdquo; for variables and methods.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-author" >The Author
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#the-author">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://web.stanford.edu/~ouster/cgi-bin/home.php">John Ousterhout&lt;/a> is a computer scientist who got his PhD from Carnegie Mellon, did some cool research work, bounced around the industry a bit, and has settled back into academia as a faculty member at Stanford where he regularly teaches courses on software design. He claims teaching this course is what gave him most of his inspiration and material in writing the book. He also thanks a group of people for their help in the book, including &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rob_Pike">Rob Pike&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.jameskoppel.com/">James Koppel&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-book" >The Book
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#the-book">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Broken down into highly structured and compact chapters, Ousterhout touches on what he considers the most crucial considerations for writing modern software. He starts out by ultimately declaring complexity to be an enemy of the state of software, and anytime you find yourself writing complex code, you need to take a good look at what has led you down this demonic path.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The most fundamental problem in computer science is problem decomposition: how to take a complex problem and divide it up into pieces that can be solved independently [&amp;hellip;] we must find ways to make software simpler. Complexity will still increase over time, in spite of our best efforts, but simpler designs allow us to build larger and more powerful systems before complexity becomes overwhelming.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This problem remains prevalent no matter how much sheer willpower we have thrown at it as an industry. It seems that CS is often the &lt;em>practice&lt;/em> of independent problem solving, rather than its antagonist. Framing this as a &amp;ldquo;problem&amp;rdquo; strikes me as odd in the same way if someone told me that &amp;lsquo;math would be perfect if it weren&amp;rsquo;t for all these pesky equations&amp;rsquo;. I&amp;rsquo;m getting bogged down in semantics here, the ultimate idea is that intertwined systems lead to complexity, and complexity ultimately leads to bugs, frustration, and screaming at my computer like a lunatic when it keeps printing &lt;code>a&lt;/code> despite me &lt;em>clearly&lt;/em> telling it to print &lt;code>b&lt;/code>. Ousterhout spends the rest of the book detailing what he means by complexity, then delving into the strategies to avoid it. Each chapter details one of these strategies, providing a handy summary at the end of each one, and some red flags to watch for when you can likely implement a specific strategy to remove complexity from your design.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Every rule has its exceptions, and every principle has its limits. If you take any design idea to its extreme, you will probably end up in a bad place. Beautiful designs reflect a balance between competing ideas and approaches.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The book is staunchly opinionated on design approaches, what types of problems to focus on, and how to fix them. But it consistently warns that taking any solution to the extreme will ultimately lead you back into the clutches of complexity. And what exactly is complexity?&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Complexity is anything related to the structure of a software system that makes it hard to understand and modify the system. Complexity can take many forms. For example, it might be hard to understand how a piece of code works; it might take a lot of effort to implement a small improvement, or it might not be clear which parts of the system must be modified to make the improvement&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first symptom of complexity is that a seemingly simple change requires code modifications in many different places.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The second symptom of complexity is cognitive load, which refers to how much a developer needs to know in order to complete a task.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The third symptom of complexity is that it is not obvious which pieces of code must be modified to complete a task, or what information a developer must have to carry out the task successfully.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Of the three manifestations of complexity, unknown unknowns are the worst. An unknown unknown means that there is something you need to know, but there is no way for you to find out what it is, or even whether there is an issue.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Complexity itself is defined rather amorphously; it&amp;rsquo;s largely left to &amp;ldquo;you know it when you see it&amp;rdquo;. Which is fine for me. I&amp;rsquo;ve rarely found myself disagreeing with someone about whether some code is complex or not. Conflict usually begins when we start asking pesky questions like &amp;ldquo;how do we make it simpler?&amp;rdquo;. This question is what Ousterhout spends the majority of the book answering.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I won&amp;rsquo;t detail all of his suggestions here (take a look at the Table of Contents for a good idea), but I found his focus on comments and naming (5 of the 22 chapters) intriguing, mostly because I&amp;rsquo;ve found myself to be more focused on this aspect than nearly all of my colleagues, and often took that focus as a sign of me being somehow inferior as a programmer; that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t magically divine what the code is doing showed that I was somehow deficient. It turns out that Ousterhout agrees with me that this is something to focus heavily on, and can really help everyone. Some of his advice includes &lt;strong>starting your method by writing the comment&lt;/strong> then work on the implementation, taking care to update the comments as you make changes to the original design. This can be annoying — especially as you make lots of changes in need of documenting — but forces you to at least write &lt;em>something&lt;/em>, where most people never bother going that far.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My only real criticism of the book is the same I have for all programming books: its reliance on toy problems. Toy problems are a necessity for this stuff. You can&amp;rsquo;t just say &amp;ldquo;my example is Kubernetes, go read it&amp;rdquo;, I need digestible problems to learn your lessons from. For the concrete problems and solutions Ousterhout focuses on, this use of toy problems makes even more sense, but so often I find that simplifying the issue often trivializes the solution. So applying some of the toy code advice to a situation where I actually am working on code as large and complex as Kubernetes becomes tricky.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can see this in another light though, as Ousterhout continually mentions that the complexity we most often encounter is rarely a symptom of overall design, but rather is added in small increments over the years, until you find yourself staring at a 50 layer &lt;code>if-else&lt;/code> garbage pile. Just like no one looks like Arnold Schwarzenegger after a couple days in the gym, and Schwarzenegger doesn&amp;rsquo;t gain 50 pounds of fat after eating a bag of chips, these large transitions usually take time. It&amp;rsquo;s those little decisions, like choosing to comment your code, spend a little more investment on a simpler design, focusing on more-frequent use cases on that one method, those little acts of care add up to reduce overall complexity as long as you consistently adhere to their underlying philosophy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-takeaways" >The Takeaways
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#the-takeaways">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>The book is excellent. I found myself silently nodding to myself as I read over written forms of lessons I had long ago internalized in my experience of writing software. I wish I had read it sooner, and I think that if you&amp;rsquo;re a college senior embarking on your career — or have been working for a few years — this book is ideal. Here&amp;rsquo;s a scattering of key quotes and takeaways I felt to be poignant.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>it’s worth taking a little extra time to find a simple design for each new class; rather than implementing the first idea that comes to mind, try a couple of alternative designs and pick the cleanest one. Try to imagine a few ways in which the system might need to be changed in the future and make sure that will be easy with your design.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I find this can sometimes paralyze me with decision paralysis though. Best to not be taken to the extreme.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>interfaces should be designed to make the common case as simple as possible&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>An opinionated book recommends you use an opinionated design. Though sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s tricky to predict just how exactly people will use your code.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Information leakage is one of the most important red flags in software design. One of the best skills you can learn as a software designer is a high level of sensitivity to information leakage. If you encounter information leakage between classes, ask yourself “How can I reorganize these classes so that this particular piece of knowledge only affects a single class?”&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>I have found over and over that specialization leads to complexity; I now think that over-specialization may be the single greatest cause of complexity in software. Conversely, code that is more general-purpose is simpler, cleaner, and easier to understand.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>I have noticed that the design-it-twice principle is sometimes hard for really smart people to embrace. When they are growing up, smart people discover that their first quick idea about any problem is sufficient for a good grade; there is no need to consider a second or third possibility. This tends to result in bad work habits. However, as these people get older, they get promoted into environments with harder and harder problems. Eventually, everyone reaches a point where your first ideas are no longer good enough; if you want to get really great results, you have to consider a second possibility, or perhaps a third, no matter how smart you are. The design of large software systems falls in this category: no-one is good enough to get it right with their first try.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>If you want to maintain a clean design for a system, you must take a strategic approach when modifying existing code. Ideally, when you have finished with each change, the system will have the structure it would have had if you had designed it from the start with that change in mind.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I love this idea, but it&amp;rsquo;s hard to focus on when this change is blocking 5 different teams that need it now.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Don’t change existing conventions. Resist the urge to “improve” on existing conventions. Having a “better idea” is not a sufficient excuse to introduce inconsistencies. Your new idea may indeed be better, but the value of consistency over inconsistency is almost always greater than the value of one approach over another.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Consistency == Readability&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Programmers’ intuitions about performance are unreliable. This is true even for experienced developers. If you start making changes based on intuition, you’ll waste time on things that don’t actually improve performance, and you’ll probably make the system more complicated in the process.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Design it, then measure it to find out where you fucked up.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Use Longer Fucking Variable Names</title><link>https://kalverra.github.io/programming/use-longer-fucking-variable-names/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kalverra.github.io/programming/use-longer-fucking-variable-names/</guid><description>&lt;p>Really, please just do it. I see this crap in so many different repos, written by otherwise amazingly good developers. A recent &lt;a href="https://go.dev/">Go&lt;/a> example:&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-go" data-lang="go">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">p&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">err&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">:=&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">picFunc&lt;/span>()
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;hr>
&lt;p>What the hell am I supposed to do with this? You know that computers have multiple terabytes of storage now right? What&amp;rsquo;s the bullshit excuse for just using &lt;code>e&lt;/code>?&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;em>I&amp;rsquo;m saving storage space&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>You aren&amp;rsquo;t programming the goddamn space shuttle, it&amp;rsquo;s a bot that posts cat pictures on Instagram. You can spare a couple megabytes on your source code files.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-go" data-lang="go">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">pic&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">err&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">:=&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">picFunc&lt;/span>()
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Okay better, but what&amp;rsquo;s the pic?&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;em>The pic from the function&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Just pretend I don&amp;rsquo;t know what you&amp;rsquo;re talking about, and imagine me asking you &amp;ldquo;what the hell are you talking about?&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-go" data-lang="go">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">thePicFromThePicFunc&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">err&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">:=&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">picFunc&lt;/span>()
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;em>I don&amp;rsquo;t understand what you want from me&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Try to consider some descriptions of the object that the variable is pointing to. Imagine I&amp;rsquo;m constantly asking you what the variable is for, how it can be used, and why you need it.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-go" data-lang="go">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">thePicFromThePicFuncThatHoldsAPicToUseForLater&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">err&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">:=&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">picFunc&lt;/span>()
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Okay, let&amp;rsquo;s maybe just concentrate on &lt;strong>what&lt;/strong> a &lt;code>pic&lt;/code> is. A &lt;code>picture&lt;/code>? What kind of one?&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-go" data-lang="go">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">catPicture&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">err&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">:=&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">picFunc&lt;/span>()
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Great! What&amp;rsquo;s the context around the cat picture? What info would help me figure out what I can do with the cat picture?&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-go" data-lang="go">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">latestCatPicture&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">err&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">:=&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">picFunc&lt;/span>()
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;hr>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m so proud.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;em>What about &lt;code>err&lt;/code>?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>You name that anything else and I think the Go gopher will manifest itself from your screen and slap you across the face.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="and-write-more-comments-while-youre-at-it" >And Write More Comments While You&amp;rsquo;re At It
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#and-write-more-comments-while-youre-at-it">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>They&amp;rsquo;re easy, I promise. Write an algorithm that looks weird? Just tell me why it has 19 nested for loops. Don&amp;rsquo;t assume I&amp;rsquo;ll figure it out or read the docs or some other ridiculous assumptions.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-go" data-lang="go">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">// Assigns a variable and and error from calling picFunc()
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">p&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">err&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">:=&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">picFunc&lt;/span>()
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Go fuck yourself.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Being a Great SDET</title><link>https://kalverra.github.io/programming/good-testers-are-good-devs/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kalverra.github.io/programming/good-testers-are-good-devs/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="what-an-sdet-does" >What an SDET Does
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#what-an-sdet-does">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>An SDET is a bit of a niche position in the tech world that focuses on testing software. You don&amp;rsquo;t have the time or resources to wait for a team of manual testers figure out what you broke every time you refactor a method. So instead, you get a couple SDETs like myself to write a program to test your system with blazing speed. So every time you move a button to the left a bit, you can be sure that you didn&amp;rsquo;t somehow also break half of your site. Most of SDETS work with developers and manual testers, figuring out how the system SHOULD work, and then finding a way to programmatically ensure that.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-an-sdet-needs-to-be-good-at" >What an SDET Needs to Be Good At
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#what-an-sdet-needs-to-be-good-at">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Development.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That&amp;rsquo;s number 1, without a doubt. An SDET&amp;rsquo;s goal is to test a system quickly and thoroughly, and to do that you need to design a program that can do all the following:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Run as quickly as possible&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Concisely report what went wrong and why&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Easily understood by other developers and testers who want to test it&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Is easily expandable to account for new features and test cases&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>All these traits require you to develop good software. The only big difference between an SDET and a typical developer is the goal and customers. Your goal is to find all the ways the system can break, and your customers are the developers who need to know what&amp;rsquo;s breaking so they can fix it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The second most important skill is where the testing mindset comes into play. You need to be good at spotting edge cases, covering scenarios where things might fall apart, and prioritizing the tests that will bring the team the greatest amount of value. This all means gaining a deep understanding of how the system you&amp;rsquo;re testing works.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s not for everyone, you&amp;rsquo;re rarely the star of the show. I often describe it as playing the support or healing character in a role-playing game. You&amp;rsquo;re rarely at the front of everyone&amp;rsquo;s mind, but when you&amp;rsquo;re not around, it&amp;rsquo;s immediately evident.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Cryptocurrencies For the Non-Technical</title><link>https://kalverra.github.io/tech-explainers/cryptocurrencies/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kalverra.github.io/tech-explainers/cryptocurrencies/</guid><description>&lt;p>Cryptocurrencies have entered the public consciousness. Super Bowl 56 aired ads from &lt;a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/02/14/1080237873/superbowl-ads-crypto-bitcoin">cryptocurrency companies&lt;/a>, and sports stadiums have been named after &lt;a href="https://www.nbcsports.com/washington/nationals/nationals-accept-cryptocurrency-ballpark-early-2023-season">similar&lt;/a> &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crypto.com_Arena">organizations&lt;/a>. Local and national news outlets&amp;rsquo; coverage of these events — laden with technical jargon that is often laughably misused — often makes audiences turn to their nearest tech-literate acquaintance and ask, &amp;ldquo;what are those exactly?&amp;rdquo;. As a member of the the tech-literate, I&amp;rsquo;m consistently disappointed with my answer to this question. It&amp;rsquo;s often half-assed and satisfies neither me nor my less-than-captive audience. So here&amp;rsquo;s my attempt at a high-quality answer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Disclaimer&lt;/strong>: I&amp;rsquo;ve been working seriously in the cryptocurrency space for a little over a year. That&amp;rsquo;s a relatively long time given how new this tech is, but I&amp;rsquo;m not an expert. Also, while I work on a cryptocurrency project, all opinions are solely my own, and I&amp;rsquo;m sure my co-workers would vehemently argue against at least a few of them.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="how-they-work" >How They Work
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#how-they-work">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>You don&amp;rsquo;t need to know how cryptocurrencies work to use them; just like you can use your credit card without intimate knowledge of how the banking system works. As the technology matures, it will become simpler for the layperson to use and understand. It&amp;rsquo;s for this reason that I find most cryptocurrency explanations to a general audience lean far too technical. That&amp;rsquo;s because a lot of the people in this space are tech nerds, and the tech behind cryptocurrencies is revolutionary and complex, so tech nerds believe that&amp;rsquo;s the part everyone is interested about. In reality, such explanations quickly devolve into acronyms and esoteric computer terms that bore audiences to sleep. So I&amp;rsquo;ll keep the explanation on &lt;em>how&lt;/em> this tech works brief: Math&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. Primarily a study of math and computer science called &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/jhXCTbFnK8o">cryptography&lt;/a>, thus the name &lt;em>crypto-currencies&lt;/em> (often abbreviated to &lt;em>crypto&lt;/em>).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>An important aspect to understand is that cryptocurrencies live on a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blockchain">blockchain&lt;/a>. A blockchain is&amp;hellip; well a chain of blocks, each block containing a record of transactions between people. New transactions get put into these blocks and added on to the chain. There is no single, capital B blockchain, and multiple currencies can live on a single chain. Most people have heard of&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> the O.G. chain and currency, &lt;a href="https://bitcoin.org/en/">Bitcoin&lt;/a>, but there are hundreds more blockchains and millions more currencies now. Many in the crypto community actually consider Bitcoin a bit of a relic&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>, and the blockchain technology most people are working on now is &lt;a href="https://ethereum.org/en/">Ethereum&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-theyre-important" >Why They&amp;rsquo;re Important
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#why-theyre-important">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Cryptocurrencies have some unique traits that distinguish them from normal currencies, primarily that they are decentralized. Unlike typical currencies, there is no central entity that controls the currency or its operation&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. No government or bank can decide to print more or less of the currency, and if you want to change how the currency is issued or operates, you usually need to propose such changes for a vote by the community. And if a government wants to shut down or ban cryptocurrencies, it&amp;rsquo;s near impossible, as the people operating the blockchain are scattered around the world, and hard to find anyway.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The blockchain world is also predicated on the idea of trustless technologies. You can mathematically verify everything, read the code of companies you interact with, and &lt;a href="https://etherscan.io/">see every program and transaction&lt;/a> that happens on the blockchain&lt;sup id="fnref:5">&lt;a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. You may say &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know the math, I&amp;rsquo;m just trusting you that&amp;rsquo;s the case!&amp;rdquo;. Sure, but you can learn the math, or go to another person that knows the math, or use a program that confirms it. Whereas no matter how long I ask Goldman Sachs to show me their books, they keep blowing me off, telling me disrespectful things like &amp;ldquo;who are you?&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;please stop drinking liquor and yelling at our office&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup id="fnref:6">&lt;a href="#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">6&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. On a blockchain you can see every transaction your bank or government or anyone has ever made, all while drinking liquor and yelling at your cellphone instead of a big office building.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s not just transactions that happen on this public chain, but also programs. You can write a program (called a &lt;a href="https://ethereum.org/en/developers/docs/smart-contracts/">smart contract&lt;/a>) and put it on the blockchain as well. From there, anyone in the world can read the code of the program and execute it if they so choose. This enables entire companies and governments to operate on the blockchain, putting their products and services out for anyone on the chain to use.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is a fundamental shift in not only how currencies usually work, but also how technology usually works&lt;sup id="fnref:7">&lt;a href="#fn:7" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">7&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. Any time something like that happens, the tech and finance nerds emerge from their basements to tell anyone and everyone about it. It&amp;rsquo;s especially exciting because the banking industry has long been behind the times when it comes to technical innovation, and this crypto business has thrown a giant wrench in the normal state of affairs for them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What if you trust your government or bank to make good monetary decisions? Well, I&amp;rsquo;d encourage you to be a &lt;a href="https://foreignpolicy.com/2021/01/28/report-transparency-international-corruption-worst-decade-united-states/">bit less trusting&lt;/a>, but also to realize that many people don&amp;rsquo;t have that option. Cryptocurrencies and smart contracts enable people in developing countries — who typically have low trust in their country&amp;rsquo;s government and businesses — to use services like &lt;a href="https://www.coindesk.com/business/2021/12/14/accuweather-taps-chainlink-to-explore-crop-insurance-and-more/">crop insurance&lt;/a> without fear of being scammed or having the terms of their contracts change
on a whim. These benefits will start to become more and more attractive in more developed countries as businesses and governments see that they can reduce risks with them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What if you &lt;strong>want&lt;/strong> your transactions to be private? Well, you&amp;rsquo;re in luck, everything on blockchains is pseudonymous. Transactions don&amp;rsquo;t look like &lt;code>Adam paid Meg $5&lt;/code>. &lt;a href="https://etherscan.io/tx/0x01e2784e34ff05d1cf01a8d8dfe6fddbdce2e1495f3056973d8f81c2b5e72dfa">Here&amp;rsquo;s a recent transaction&lt;/a> on Ethereum:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-txt" data-lang="txt">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>0xa15a3dda54758f447ce55873d46103cc860ca0f9
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>paid
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>0xa57976422edafff7d3545a6b58150afdd9e59faf
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>0.021 Ether ($63.50)
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>&lt;code>0xa15a3dda54758f447ce55873d46103cc860ca0f9&lt;/code> is an address, and that is how you send money around in a blockchain, by sending from your address to others. They function a bit like usernames on sites like Reddit or Twitter. You can make it your real name if you like, or just name yourself &lt;code>420cat420&lt;/code> and leave it at that.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Here&amp;rsquo;s primarily where we step into &amp;ldquo;Adam&amp;rsquo;s Personal Opinion Zone&amp;rdquo;. Ye be warned.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="what-they-could-become" >What They Could Become
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#what-they-could-become">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Most people&lt;sup id="fnref:8">&lt;a href="#fn:8" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">8&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> working in the space see cryptocurrencies as a turning point in tech and society, much like the internet was. In fact, many call the world of blockchains and cryptocurrencies &amp;ldquo;Web 3.0&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The counterpoint I most hear is that crypto is a fad, or a solution looking for a problem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;img src="https://i.imgur.com/sNebp1W.gif" alt="Yeah? Well, you know, that&amp;amp;rsquo;s just like, your opinion, man">
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At a minimum, cryptocurrencies have, and will, further disrupt how transactions work. There&amp;rsquo;s a massive infrastructure dedicated to moving money around that is antiquated, slow, and only gets more complicated when you cross national borders. These are all classic indicators that technology can optimize and replace the current system. Cryptocurrencies do things — like confirm payments — in seconds that take traditional banking and finance days.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>People sometimes scoff at cryptocurrencies as a stupid tech nerd thing that isn&amp;rsquo;t useful to them. To that, I present to you a clip of Bill Gates trying to explain the internet to David Letterman in 1995.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/gipL_CEw-fk" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Doesn&amp;rsquo;t sound too revolutionary does it? Bill Gates, the king of computer nerds and one of the greatest businessmen in the world, was only able to think of radio and email as the future of the internet. Back then it was normal to be skeptical of this nerdy internet thing, but if you ask &amp;ldquo;what is that internet thing anyway?&amp;rdquo; you&amp;rsquo;re typically met with looks of confusion or pity. Back then it was a niche technology that only nerds got excited about, and now the internet dominates our modern society.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But there&amp;rsquo;s a problem with the internet today: ads. They are the reason Google makes $257.6 billion a year, and they are the reason why tech companies like Google collect a &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/wqn3gR1WTcA">frightening amount of information&lt;/a> about you. Targeting ads based on your personal data is a lucrative business, and a precursor to some dystopian &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/5470.1984">1984&lt;/a> shit. You remember how terrifying that book was? Or how dark the SparkNotes summary sounded when you were cramming before that 10th grade English class? Cryptocurrencies and blockchains enable different profit models, ones that don&amp;rsquo;t depend on collecting your personal data and selling it to the highest bidder.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Humans are notoriously bad at predicting the future, so only time will tell the truth. But some exciting areas that cryptocurrencies could revolutionize include &lt;a href="https://vitalik.ca/general/2021/05/25/voting2.html">voting&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://vitalik.ca/general/2021/10/31/cities.html">cities&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://blog.chain.link/blockchain-insurance/">insurance&lt;/a>, banks, and modern internet infrastructure.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="faq" >FAQ
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#faq">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;h3 id="how-can-i-use-them-right-now" >How Can I Use Them Right Now?
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#how-can-i-use-them-right-now">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>I suspect things will drastically change in the next 10 or 20 years, but for now the use of these technologies is primarily regulated to early-adopters and builders that are deep into technology or finance. Things like currency exchanges, loans, gambling, and video games&lt;sup id="fnref:9">&lt;a href="#fn:9" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">9&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> dominate the current crypto world, and most of them require some detailed tech knowledge to use correctly. There&amp;rsquo;s not much, that I know of, for the casual observer to do with the crypto world, &lt;em>right now&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="nfts" >NFTs?
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#nfts">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>I think current iterations are kinda dumb.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For those uninitiated to the latest tech news cycle, blockchain technology enables owning not only currency, but damn near anything. Currency is &lt;a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/f/fungibility.asp#:~:text=Key%20Takeaways-,Fungibility%20is%20the%20ability%20of%20a%20good%20or%20asset%20to,houses%2C%20are%20non%2Dfungible.">fungible&lt;/a>, meaning that a one dollar bill isn&amp;rsquo;t worth more than another one dollar bill. As far as the typical consumer is concerned, they&amp;rsquo;re identical in value and usage. NFTs are &lt;strong>N&lt;/strong>on-&lt;strong>F&lt;/strong>ungible &lt;strong>T&lt;/strong>okens, meaning they&amp;rsquo;re unique.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All this is to say that you can use blockchain tech to show your ownership of unique objects like &lt;a href="https://www.theverge.com/22310188/nft-explainer-what-is-blockchain-crypto-art-faq">art&lt;/a>. Frankly, the art market &lt;a href="https://freakonomics.com/podcast/a-fascinating-sexy-intellectually-compelling-unregulated-global-market/">could use some disruption&lt;/a>, but what troubles me is how the crypto community tries to proselytize art NFTs as the big crypto thing. NFTs have some interesting uses like replacing typical land and house deeds, but showing people a picture of a cruddy, pixilated avatar and saying &amp;ldquo;see, the future!&amp;rdquo; is, at the least, lacking in creativity. It seems to me like trying to convince someone that Baseball is a cool sport to watch, and then showing them all you baseball trading cards to convince them.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="environmental-impact" >Environmental Impact?
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#environmental-impact">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s not great. The process most blockchains use to operate is a &lt;a href="https://ethereum.org/en/developers/docs/consensus-mechanisms/">consensus mechanism&lt;/a> called Proof-of-Work, which entails people running very expensive and energy inefficient programs&lt;sup id="fnref:10">&lt;a href="#fn:10" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">10&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> on their computers. But, there&amp;rsquo;s hope that this will change soon. Proof-of-Stake is a method that blockchains can use that consumes 99% less electricity, and most new chains use it. Others like Ethereum are &lt;a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2022/03/04/1046636/ethereum-blockchain-proof-of-stake/#:~:text=Of%20course%2C%20Ethereum's%20move%20to,such%20a%20model%20is%20complex.">actively working&lt;/a> to switch to this system.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="money-laundering" >Money Laundering?
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#money-laundering">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s harder than you think. The blockchain is completely open, and a permanent record of every transaction ever made. Money launderers aren&amp;rsquo;t huge fans of having all their transactions publicly available by any FBI agent or teenager who cares to take a look. That said, blockchains are &lt;a href="https://www.thefreedictionary.com/pseudononymous">pseudonymous&lt;/a>, meaning that you can easily hide your real-life identity on the blockchain, but there&amp;rsquo;s not a lot of options for turning your crypto currency into hard cash without alerting the government.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="hacks-and-scams" >Hacks and Scams?
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#hacks-and-scams">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Scams are unfortunately common in the crypto world right now. This is a symptom of the technology being new, and people not really knowing how things work. Most of them essentially boil down to &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rsquo;re the password police and need to ask you some questions&amp;rdquo;. Hopefully improving the user experience and knowledge will improve things.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Hacks in the crypto world are currently getting a lot of publicity thanks to the massive amounts of money that are being stolen. This is another symptom of new technology, meaning that people are still figuring out the pitfalls and security loopholes. Blockchain tech also has the unique property of being totally open, meaning that a hacker can often see all the code of the thing they&amp;rsquo;re trying to hack, information that most hackers would kill for. It also means that people know when these hacks happen immediately, as all these things are public. A lot of companies, when hacked, will do their best to cover it up. Cryptocurrency projects lack that privilege.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="taxes" >Taxes?
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#taxes">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s&amp;hellip; complicated. Most tax lawyers don&amp;rsquo;t know what&amp;rsquo;s going on most of the time, and legislation is changing all the time. Suffice to say that any time you turn cryptocurrency into real cash, the government knows, and will ask for their cut.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="dogecoin-and-elon-musk" >Dogecoin and Elon Musk?
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#dogecoin-and-elon-musk">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s also complicated, but less so. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dogecoin">Dogecoin&lt;/a> is a cryptocurrency that was created as a sort of in-joke among crypto people. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t serve any purpose except as a weird techie joke, and it hit mainstream recognition when Elon Musk &lt;a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Business/dogecoin-rallies-elon-musk-tweet/story?id=82265024">tweeted&lt;/a> about it. People got it in their minds that since tech genius Elon Musk was talking about Dogecoin, it must be a sound investment. It&amp;rsquo;s not. He was either joking, or &lt;a href="https://vitalik.ca/general/2021/05/23/scaling.html">is wrong&lt;/a>. There have been recent attempts to actually revive the project and turn it into something worthwhile, we&amp;rsquo;ll see where that goes.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="should-i-invest--what-should-i-invest-in" >Should I Invest / What Should I Invest In?
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#should-i-invest--what-should-i-invest-in">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>I can&amp;rsquo;t tell you / I can&amp;rsquo;t tell you. I &lt;strong>can&lt;/strong> tell you that you should probably should invest in something, but for the majority of people, cryptocurrencies are probably not that something&lt;sup id="fnref:11">&lt;a href="#fn:11" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">11&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. The crypto markets are uniquely risky, and most currencies aren&amp;rsquo;t really designed to be investment vehicles anyway. There are thousands of YouTubers, bloggers, and podcasters that will promise untold crypto riches if you listen to their sure-thing advice where they show some fancy charts and make insane predictions. They&amp;rsquo;re lying, either to you or themselves.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There&amp;rsquo;s lots of speculation on cryptocurrency prices now, and currently not a whole lot of mainstream functionality exists, leading to more speculation of a possible &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dot-com_bubble">dot-com style bubble&lt;/a>. Suffice to say that if you&amp;rsquo;re reading this post to explain cryptocurrencies to a beginner, there are a lot more steps to take on educating yourself before you try to invest in these projects.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="im-interested-where-can-i-learn-more" >I&amp;rsquo;m interested, Where Can I Learn More?
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#im-interested-where-can-i-learn-more">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Chainlink has &lt;a href="https://www.smartcontracthub.dev/">set up a hub&lt;/a> to help people learn more about the tech. Chainlink Labs&amp;rsquo;s CEO, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/sergeynazarov?lang=en">Sergey Nazarov&lt;/a>, did a &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/TPXTmVdlyoc">long interview&lt;/a> last year on these topics.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vitalik_Buterin">Vitalik Buterin&lt;/a>, the key figure behind Ethereum, does a lot of outreach. He has done &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/3x1b_S6Qp2Q">some&lt;/a> &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/XW0QZmtbjvs">interviews&lt;/a> that non-techies should find approachable. He also does some deep technical writing on &lt;a href="https://vitalik.ca/">his website&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Gary Gensler, the current head of the SEC, taught a course at MIT on the finance side of blockchains and cryptocurrency that is available for free &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLUl4u3cNGP63UUkfL0onkxF6MYgVa04Fn">on YouTube&lt;/a>. It&amp;rsquo;s long, but invaluable resource.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="im-interested-how-can-i-work-on-this-stuff" >I&amp;rsquo;m Interested, How Can I Work On This Stuff?
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#im-interested-how-can-i-work-on-this-stuff">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>You&amp;rsquo;re in luck, demand is high! Chainlink &lt;a href="https://chainlinklabs.com/careers">is hiring&lt;/a> for nearly everything right now, and there&amp;rsquo;s plenty of others &lt;a href="https://cryptocurrencyjobs.co/">looking for&lt;/a> eager employees.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;d actually like to learn more deeply about the technology behind cryptocurrencies, check out &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/bBC-nXj3Ng4">this excellent video&lt;/a> that doesn&amp;rsquo;t require any background in math or computer science.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>Lots of people haven&amp;rsquo;t heard of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satoshi_Nakamoto">Satoshi Nakamoto&lt;/a> though, the creator of the coin. Their story is an interesting one, because no one knows who they are. The name is a pseudonym, and there&amp;rsquo;s some guesses, but no definitive reveal as to who this person actually is (they also stopped posting in 2010). As such, some people in the crypto community elect to do something similar, and are only identified by their online profile names.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3">
&lt;p>Those who think Bitcoin is &lt;strong>not&lt;/strong> a relic often like to write mean things on the internet about people who say otherwise. It&amp;rsquo;s a whole culture war I won&amp;rsquo;t get into.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4">
&lt;p>There are some rare situations where this isn&amp;rsquo;t the case, like when a company has their own private implementation, or when a scammer is trying to swindle you out of your money.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:5">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/monero-project/monero">Monero&lt;/a> is a notable exception to this rule, but it&amp;rsquo;s rather fringe. It&amp;rsquo;s a cryptocurrency project that hides account balances and transactions.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:6">
&lt;p>Those fascist pigs&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:7">
&lt;p>Not the drunkenly yelling at your cell phone though, that mostly stays the same.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:7" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:8">
&lt;p>It was far more common in the early days for anarchists and libertarians to assert that the invention of Bitcoin and similar currencies would be the turning point for revolution, that the world would now operate without governments entirely. The crypto community still skews libertarian by its nature, but most have disposed of the whole &amp;ldquo;completely dismantle all governments&amp;rdquo; idea. Most focus on just partially dismantling governments and mostly dismantling banks.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:8" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:9">
&lt;p>As an avid gamer, these are pretty lame. Personally I don&amp;rsquo;t think video games and cryptocurrencies will mix very well in the future, but I guess we&amp;rsquo;ll see.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:9" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:10">
&lt;p>This process often uses a specialized piece of computer hardware called a GPU, or graphics card. They&amp;rsquo;re typically used by people who do a lot of visual work on their computers like animations and 3D models. They&amp;rsquo;re also used by people like me who play a lot of video games on their computer. So I&amp;rsquo;m very eager for Proof-of-Stake to happen for not only environmental reasons, but also because people keep buying all the graphics cards and I cannot get one to play games with!&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:10" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:11">
&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;d like to learn about investing strategies and how markets work, &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40242274-a-random-walk-down-wall-street">these&lt;/a> &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/106835.The_Intelligent_Investor">books&lt;/a> &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/38315.Fooled_by_Randomness">are&lt;/a> &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/381355.The_Bogleheads_Guide_to_Investing">great&lt;/a>. Here&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/personalfinance/wiki/investing">cheat-sheet&lt;/a> if you&amp;rsquo;re not quite that &lt;em>invested&lt;/em> in the topic.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:11" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>About</title><link>https://kalverra.github.io/about/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kalverra.github.io/about/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;img src="https://kalverra.github.io/images/head_shot.jpeg" alt="Me">
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m Adam, a Software Engineer currently working on &lt;a href="https://chain.link/">Chainlink&lt;/a> (anything I say is personal opinion, etc&amp;hellip;). You can check out my work on my &lt;a href="https://github.com/kalverra">GitHub&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/adam-hamrick-8b1866116/">LinkedIn&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Partially wanting to improve my writing, and partially inspired by &lt;a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/words.html">this Paul Graham essay&lt;/a>, I decided to start this. I’m making it public to force some accountability. And who knows, maybe someday I’ll say something interesting enough that someone other than my mom will want to read it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-im-doing-now" >What I&amp;rsquo;m Doing Now
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#what-im-doing-now">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&amp;#x1f468;&amp;zwj;&amp;#x1f4bc; Working on &lt;a href="https://chain.link/">Chainlink&lt;/a>, namely focusing on improving our quality standards, automated testing and release process, and ensuring that we actually work on all the chains we want to work on. It&amp;rsquo;s hard, interesting work that I&amp;rsquo;m passionate about.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>:graduation_cap: Taking &lt;a href="https://github.com/kalverra/mit-distributed-systems">MIT&amp;rsquo;s Distributed Systems&lt;/a> course on my weeknights. I&amp;rsquo;ve learned a lot of these concepts as a consequence of work, but feel a more formal, academic approach could be helpful.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>:person_lifting_weights: I&amp;rsquo;ve taken up regular weightlifting again after a long hiatus of injury, laziness, and COVID.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;#x1f4d6; &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/110709291-adam-hamrick">Reading&lt;/a> when I can. Right now it&amp;rsquo;s sporadic, and focused on making myself more productive, but hopefully I&amp;rsquo;ll allow myself to read some fiction again.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="what-i-want-to-do-soon" >What I Want to Do Soon
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#what-i-want-to-do-soon">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/list/110709291?shelf=to-read">More reading&lt;/a>, my pile grows infinitely. Specifically I want to take another crack at &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/23463279-designing-data-intensive-applications">Designing Data-Intensive Applications&lt;/a> which I got about a quarter of the way through and had to stop as I was absorbing so little. It demands a far more attentive read.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>More rigorous crypto study, specifically I&amp;rsquo;ve heard that Stanford&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://www.coursera.org/learn/crypto">Cryptography 1&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.coursera.org/learn/crypto2">2&lt;/a> are great courses.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://blog.qtum.org/diving-into-the-ethereum-vm-6e8d5d2f3c30">Diving into the EVM&lt;/a> after I&amp;rsquo;ve got some more Solidity chops.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.startupschool.org/">Startup School&lt;/a> to help cultivate my ever-present-but-never-executed ambitions to strike out with my own company.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol></description></item><item><title>College is a Scam*</title><link>https://kalverra.github.io/essays/college-is-a-scam/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 19:26:51 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kalverra.github.io/essays/college-is-a-scam/</guid><description>&lt;p>I recently went to see my brother-in-law graduate from college. There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of attitudes present at any graduation event, the pride and accomplishment of so many young people and their parents easily sweeps you into a happy embrace. There&amp;rsquo;s also consequently an underlying sense of surety. The surety that these years of education and a degree signifying that fact were all good ideas. I went through the same process not too long ago and have possessed this same surety for the entirety of my life. So imagine my whiplash as I came across a Twitter tirade of intelligent and highly educated tech leaders claiming that a college degree is one big scam.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet">&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr">College is a scam, you don’t need it.&lt;br>&lt;br>- Stanford ‘00, ‘04, ‘05, ‘06 &lt;a href="https://t.co/VonzG04L0I">https://t.co/VonzG04L0I&lt;/a>&lt;/p>&amp;mdash; Balaji (@balajis) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/balajis/status/1472209100536614914?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December 18, 2021&lt;/a>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8">&lt;/script>
&lt;p>This isn&amp;rsquo;t exactly a new sentiment among tech leaders, but the idea&amp;rsquo;s recent resurgence got me thinking about the worth of a college degree in the modern U.S. Let&amp;rsquo;s break down &lt;a href="https://balajis.com/">Balaji Srinivasan&lt;/a>&amp;rsquo;s statement above.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="scam-is-harsh-but" >&amp;ldquo;Scam&amp;rdquo; is harsh, but&amp;hellip;
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#scam-is-harsh-but">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>You&amp;rsquo;ve probably heard of this thing called student loans that everyone freaks out about. You know, that massive number that fills your dreams with anxiety? The primary contributor to that is tuition, which has been on a meteoric rise for a while now. A 4 year degree from a state school will run you about $35,000 for a 4-year degree, while more elite or private institutions will have you pony up $100k+. The rising cost of school far outpaces any increase in wages.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;img src="https://educationdata.org/wp-content/uploads/78/historical-cost-of-tuition-and-fees.webp" alt="cost of college">
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Not to mention, most of the time that doesn&amp;rsquo;t include things like food, rent, books, that stupid fucking clicker thing that your professor insists you NEED to buy for $60. Not only are you paying for the privilege of doing homework, you also need to keep a whole-ass person alive while doing it. Do you remember your budget in college?&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Category&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Budgeted&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Rent&lt;/td>
&lt;td>$400&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Food&lt;/td>
&lt;td>$100&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Weed&lt;/td>
&lt;td>$100&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Not exactly a glamorous existence.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Adding insult to injury, free access to information has never been more prevalent. Even when I was in college classes, I would often end up learning far more about the subject from online resources than my professors.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;img src="https://i.imgur.com/NbCc7ca.jpeg" alt="Stack Overflow cap">
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If I&amp;rsquo;m paying such high costs for my education, I&amp;rsquo;d expect the quality to be equally high. The people teaching at colleges are certainly impressive, holding PHDs in their fields and generally being incredibly smart people, but I don&amp;rsquo;t need a math PHD to teach me basic calculus. If I was going to pay for a chess coach, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t hire a Grand Master. That level of expertise would cost a requisite amount of money, and at my chess level, the Grand Master wouldn&amp;rsquo;t teach me any better than some 12 year old with a couple trophies. Most colleges seem to agree with me, as they often have grad students teach undergrad courses (a practice I saw no discount on my tuition for). When you&amp;rsquo;re at a basic level, it matters a lot more on how good at &lt;em>teaching&lt;/em> the topic your instructor is, not the instructor&amp;rsquo;s own level of mastery.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The primary justification for the high costs is that a college degree will prepare you for the work force, but college isn&amp;rsquo;t an ideal job-training simulator. I went to college to become a professional programmer, but a significant portion of my time was spent in Philosophy and English classes, subjects that don&amp;rsquo;t come up too often when writing code. Even some of my computer science classes I probably could have done without entirely.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how true this is for other professions, but there&amp;rsquo;s a large disparity between the skills school teaches you and the skills companies need. I&amp;rsquo;d probably become a professional programmer faster if I had focused on problems that companies deal with instead of the problems school taught me with.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="and-you-do-need-it" >And you DO need it
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#and-you-do-need-it">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Here&amp;rsquo;s where the title&amp;rsquo;s asterisk comes in: society still values college. but the primary barrier to entry of your standard white-collar job is that piece of paper with fancy calligraphy on it. How do you plan to be hired as an accountant, engineer, or architect without a degree&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>? If you&amp;rsquo;ve already been in the industry for a while, it&amp;rsquo;s not likely to be a problem. You&amp;rsquo;ve gotten your foot in the door and proven your worth. But if your only credentials are a high school diploma and a list of books you&amp;rsquo;ve been reading in your parents&amp;rsquo; basement the past few years, prepare to be disappointed. There&amp;rsquo;s plenty of complex and well-paying jobs that you can obtain without a college degree; trade jobs like plumbers and electricians immediately come to mind. But if you&amp;rsquo;re a klutz like me, working with your hands is an unlikely prospect.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some professions and organizations are tolerant with hiring self-taught people, but only if you have some other way to prove you know what you&amp;rsquo;re doing. Tech is the biggest example because its barrier to entry is so low and the open-source community makes knowledge widely free and available. If a fresh high school grad came to me with a few projects she could speak passionately about and discuss with me in depth, I&amp;rsquo;d have few issues in hiring her. All she needs to prove her knowledge is a computer and a &lt;a href="https://github.com/">GitHub&lt;/a> portfolio. Most other industries lack the ability to assess candidates like this, and even some tech organizations won&amp;rsquo;t bother.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is not to say this is a fair position for society to take. It&amp;rsquo;s also not implying that the piece of paper, and the requisite acknowledgement of your competence from corporate America, is all that college is good for (we&amp;rsquo;ll get to that later). It&amp;rsquo;s to say that in today&amp;rsquo;s world, there&amp;rsquo;s far cheaper and more effective ways to obtain an education, but corporate America is slow to adapt. So the traditional degree is largely still a requirement, even if it&amp;rsquo;s not the most optimal way to prepare for the workforce.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;img src="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Gates#/media/File:Bill_Gates_2017_%28cropped%29.jpg" alt="William Doors">
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>People always like to point to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Gates">Bill Gates&lt;/a> (or &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Zuckerberg">Zuckerberg&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Dell">Dell&lt;/a>) as a reason to not go to college, it obviously worked out for him. His path is not a consistent one to emulate, and Bill himself encourages people to &lt;a href="https://www.gatesnotes.com/Education/11-Million-College-Grads">not be like him&lt;/a>. These people are the results of exceptional intelligence, motivation, and luck. Lacking any of those three will lead to failure for 99% of people.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="its-not-all-about-the-money" >It&amp;rsquo;s Not All About the Money
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#its-not-all-about-the-money">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>College isn&amp;rsquo;t the most efficient job training simulator because it wasn&amp;rsquo;t designed to be. It&amp;rsquo;s meant to help you grow as a person with broad intellectual achievement. And you get to do so in an environment with tons of other smart, young people looking to learn and have fun. That time I spent in English, Philosophy and Biology classes in college didn&amp;rsquo;t do much of anything for my programming abilities, but that time taught me how to be a more well-rounded human, and how to think critically about the world around me.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>I submit that this is what the real, no bullshit value of your liberal
arts education is supposed to be about: how to keep from going through
your comfortable, prosperous, respectable adult life dead, unconscious, a
slave to your head and to your natural default setting of being uniquely,
completely, imperially alone day in and day out.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ndash; &lt;em>This is Water by David Foster Wallace&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>If your dream is to become a doctor or lawyer, where you&amp;rsquo;re usually legally obligated to have a certain college degree, expect to be laughed out of every interview. If you ever manage to get that far.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item></channel></rss>