<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Books on Adam's Writing Thing</title><link>https://kalverra.github.io/books/</link><description>Adam's Writing Thing (Books)</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kalverra.github.io/books/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Review: Going Infinite</title><link>https://kalverra.github.io/books/review-going-infinite/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kalverra.github.io/books/review-going-infinite/</guid><description>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m a huge &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Lewis">Michael Lewis&lt;/a> stan. I&amp;rsquo;ve loved every book of his I&amp;rsquo;ve read (and all the movies based on them), and frequently listen to &lt;a href="https://www.pushkin.fm/podcasts/against-the-rules">his podcast&lt;/a>. I also have worked as a software developer for a cryptocurrency project for almost three years. So when I saw these two interests of mine colliding in &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/156552773-going-infinite">Going Infinite&lt;/a>, I slammed that pre-order button hard and finished this book within a week, light speed for me these days. The book details the rise and collapse of Sam Bankman-Fried (SBF) and his crypto exchange, FTX. If you&amp;rsquo;re here, I&amp;rsquo;m assuming you have at least the basics of the story. So I want to focus less on the quality of the book (from a narrative standpoint, it&amp;rsquo;s pretty good, albeit not my favorite of Lewis&amp;rsquo;s), and more about the discussion it sparked.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sbf-is-human" >SBF is Human
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#sbf-is-human">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>There&amp;rsquo;s been a lot of criticism directed at Lewis for this book, primarily because he was at least partially sympathetic towards SBF, both as a person, and about SBF&amp;rsquo;s side of the story when it comes to the collapse. Mostly I&amp;rsquo;m seeing a lot of people that are upset that SBF was painted as an odd human being, rather than the caricature of a sociopathic fraudster that everyone has already determined SBF to be&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. I have a few problems with this:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>You&amp;rsquo;re misunderstanding the point of Michael Lewis, he&amp;rsquo;s not an investigative journalist or a judge searching for scandal, he&amp;rsquo;s a writer who has a knack for finding interesting, complexly human characters amidst unusual circumstances.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I don&amp;rsquo;t think it&amp;rsquo;s particularly flattering towards SBF at all.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The book doesn&amp;rsquo;t attempt to absolve him of anything the U.S. government has accused him of.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>There&amp;rsquo;s been accusations that Sam put Lewis under his spell, and uses that visionary-jedi-mind-trick shit that &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_Holmes">Elizabeth Holmes&lt;/a> was &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jonwu_/status/1433595857304055814">still pulling off&lt;/a> even after Theranos went kaput. Or even that Lewis was wowed into loving SBF after being brought to ritzy parties with Leonardo DiCaprio and Hillary Clinton&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. Or even more ridiculously, that Lewis was bribed by SBF to portray him positively&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. I think Lewis was certainly fascinated by Sam, and tried to paint him as a human being (as much as he can resemble one) with plenty of flaws, and also as someone who would most definitely risk a bunch of money that he should not have been risking.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sbf-is-compelling" >SBF Is Compelling
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#sbf-is-compelling">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Lewis spends a lot of time on SBF&amp;rsquo;s positive qualities. He paints SBF as interesting and intelligent, a curious case of someone with almost negative charisma that turns it around into dazzling sophisticated investors and media types with his brilliance and quirkiness. This is a perfect character for Lewis, but I&amp;rsquo;ve heard a lot of people claim that mentioning these parts of SBF at all is proof that Lewis sees SBF as innocent or an overall good person. Or that Lewis is lying about these traits purely to puff up SBF. This is part of what I&amp;rsquo;m talking about that people have created a caricature of pure evil and negativity that SBF must match, or else Lewis is a fraud. If SBF wasn&amp;rsquo;t smart and compelling, none of us would be here. The same way Jobs bedazzled audiences with his vision and intelligence while being a raging asshole behind closed doors, SBF was an interesting person who managed to charm plenty of people, who also happened to have massive character flaws. Calling SBF intelligent, a good trader, or an interesting person to talk to doesn&amp;rsquo;t deny that he can also be a manipulative, irresponsible, prick. If he were just the last 3 things, I don&amp;rsquo;t think he would have gotten as far as he did, and Lewis would never have written about him.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sbf-is-a-dick" >SBF is a Dick
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#sbf-is-a-dick">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>SBF exhibits great qualities for a Wall Street trader; if given a good enough argument, he&amp;rsquo;ll unwaveringly commit, even if he personally has reservations. He ignores any personal hangups or emotions and follows whatever will most probably produce his desired outcome. And that desired outcome is not always bad, but he&amp;rsquo;s very ends-justify-the-means coded. He has no problem disregarding others&amp;rsquo; emotions and desires in pursuit of his own. Through how SBF treats his friends (exploiting their talents until they are no longer of use), his employees (making huge demands and failing to manage, empathize, or generally give a shit about their problems), and his girlfriend (emotionally neglecting her until he wants sex from her, then love-bombing until he gets what he wants and leaves), Lewis shows incontrovertibly that SBF is an emotionally manipulative asshole.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As far as SBF is concerned, books are stupid, boring, long, and should be shortened to a blog post. Adults are stupid too, anyone over the age of 30 has nothing useful left to say or do in their life (I wonder how this became a self-fulfilling prophecy given SBF&amp;rsquo;s conviction at the ripe age of 31). In fact, most everyone in the world is stupid besides SBF, because according to himself, SBF is a being of pure logic and thought rather than all those messy emotions that cloud judgement. Except for all those times that Lewis mentions his actions were clearly influenced by irrational emotion and lust, like when he moved the entire headquarters of FTX twice because of where his on-and-off girlfriend was located. Lewis showcases uncountable red flags in SBF&amp;rsquo;s personality, and while there is some acknowledgement of his better qualities, I don&amp;rsquo;t see how anyone could see this book as complimentary of Sam the person.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sbf-would-totally-do-illegal-shit" >SBF Would Totally Do Illegal Shit
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#sbf-would-totally-do-illegal-shit">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>He&amp;rsquo;s a gambler that has had reckless and illegal bets pay off before. It&amp;rsquo;s very clear that if he can make a bet he thinks he&amp;rsquo;ll win, he&amp;rsquo;ll take it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Alright, I&amp;rsquo;ve talked about how I think the book was good and painted SBF as a human, albeit not a sympathetic one. Now for the issues I have with it, which have grown in severity as I&amp;rsquo;ve written this.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="its-weird-lewis-didnt-mention-the-things" >It&amp;rsquo;s Weird Lewis Didn&amp;rsquo;t Mention The Thing(s)
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#its-weird-lewis-didnt-mention-the-things">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Lewis has mentioned that he left certain things out of the book because he felt it didn&amp;rsquo;t fit the story. This isn&amp;rsquo;t as sinister as it usually sounds (remember point 1 at the beginning of this), but it does remind us that he&amp;rsquo;s looking for an interesting tale, not so much an exhaustive expose to be read aloud in a court room. Even so, there are some bits that I think are pretty relevant to the story, and at the least it&amp;rsquo;s odd that Lewis doesn&amp;rsquo;t include them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Molly White &lt;a href="https://newsletter.mollywhite.net/p/review-michael-lewiss-going-infinite">goes over these omissions&lt;/a> in more detail; basically Lewis would mention something SBF did or said, but Lewis neglected to explicitly call out that the thing he did or said was immoral, illegal, or a lie. I&amp;rsquo;d be more willing to brush these omissions aside with the idea that Lewis wants to only tell the event how they happened, and not pass judgement. But in his other books, &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/26889576">The Big Short&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/46266188">The Fifth Risk&lt;/a>, and &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/56790170-the-premonition">The Premonition&lt;/a> Lewis has no problem calling organizations and individuals out as corrupt, incompetent, or evil. So while he never defends SBF&amp;rsquo;s actions&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>, he never admonishes them either. And that leaves a bad taste in my mouth now that I compare how he handled figures like Trump in his previous books.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Also, you&amp;rsquo;ve got to talk about when &lt;a href="https://www.vox.com/future-perfect/23462333/sam-bankman-fried-ftx-cryptocurrency-effective-altruism-crypto-bahamas-philanthropy">Sam Bankman-Fried tries to explain himself&lt;/a>. It&amp;rsquo;s a conversation SBF has with a reporter soon after the walls start to tumble down where he disavows his image as an effective altruist, claiming it was all just a PR stunt. In fact, all of his talks of ethics and altruism was a front for his true 4D chess match of minimizing risk to his reputation while maximizing returns to his bank account. I think this is a crucial part of SBF&amp;rsquo;s story, and for Lewis to not even mention it (the book was being written while this came out) still baffles me. Lewis&amp;rsquo; ongoing argument through the book is that SBF was nothing if not dedicated to his ideals, and while the ideals were admirable, Lewis paints SBF as a person who would do immoral, illegal, and emotionally abusive things on the road to those goals. Lewis definitely should have called out when SBF realized his goose was cooked, that he said, &amp;ldquo;nah, jk&amp;rdquo; to what those goals even were. Maybe Lewis didn&amp;rsquo;t want to include anything other than his own experience in the book? But come on man, give it a footnote at least.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="behind-the-bastards" >Behind the Bastards
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#behind-the-bastards">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m a fan of another podcast, &lt;a href="https://www.iheart.com/podcast/105-behind-the-bastards-29236323/">Behind the Bastards&lt;/a>, a wonderfully researched and funny exploration into some of history&amp;rsquo;s worst people (plus some less worse ones). They did a &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/lSbMy6vblsY?si=Srrqx-JfkaBDjbGK">short series on SBF&lt;/a> when he was under investigation, and then &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/a9tDihgEn2k?si=qBHkpFkydgIIyhbw">posted updates&lt;/a> shortly after his conviction. That 2 episode update was primarily a Michael Lewis beat down. I won&amp;rsquo;t go over all of it here, but it had some convincing arguments and information that helped sway me towards the side of Lewis being more wrong than right in his book. While it also contains some fallacies that I argue against at the beginning of this review, I found it to largely be the best critical-of-Lewis side of this argument I&amp;rsquo;ve seen.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="effective-altruism" >Effective Altruism
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#effective-altruism">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Scott Alexander&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://www.astralcodexten.com/p/in-continued-defense-of-effective">defense of effective altruism&lt;/a> is a worthy read in the face of all this. Much like Lewis&amp;rsquo; praise of SBF&amp;rsquo;s intelligence doesn&amp;rsquo;t make Lewis a fraud, SBF&amp;rsquo;s fall does not make effective altruism a fraud. I think it&amp;rsquo;s a movement that has caught a lot of undeserved stray shots in these SBF headlines. People donating their money for effective good in the world is always a win in my book, assuming they&amp;rsquo;re balancing their motives and bets.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>This seems to be running in tandem with &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/122765395-elon-musk">Walter Issacson&amp;rsquo;s biography on Elon Musk&lt;/a> which I haven&amp;rsquo;t read (yet), but have seen a lot of similar criticisms for. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t paint Musk to be an evil caricature, so that must confirm that Issacson is a Musk simp who was bribed into writing a book that does have plenty of criticism, but not an outright condemnation that people wanted.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve seen this particular accusation a few times, and always scratch my head. Lewis isn&amp;rsquo;t Brad Pitt or anything, but he&amp;rsquo;s decently famous and wealthy. Also, Brad Pitt is in 2 of the movies based on his books. He&amp;rsquo;s no famous billionaire, but it&amp;rsquo;s not as if Lewis is some shmuck who melts in the face of celebrity.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3">
&lt;p>This is an especially ludicrous and weirdly pervasive argument. See my above footnote; Lewis isn&amp;rsquo;t a billionaire, but he&amp;rsquo;s one of the most successful writers in the world who sold the movie rights to this book before it was even finished. Not only that, his family is old money rich, he&amp;rsquo;s got plenty of money. And even if SBF bribed him, with what? Lewis had front row seats to watch the money pile burn, he knows he&amp;rsquo;s not getting shit. And even if SBF had already paid, how would he hold Lewis accountable at this point?&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4">
&lt;p>Later on in his podcast about the book, he is quick to call out that SBF definitely did several illegal things, though I don&amp;rsquo;t think he mentions anything like that in the book.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Review: The Power of Habit</title><link>https://kalverra.github.io/books/review-the-power-of-habit/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kalverra.github.io/books/review-the-power-of-habit/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/12609433">The Power of Habit by Charles Duhigg&lt;/a> is the reason that I just turned on a &lt;a href="https://pomofocus.io/">Pomodoro timer&lt;/a> to write this review. He doesn&amp;rsquo;t ever mention it in his book (I think I &lt;a href="https://www.verywellmind.com/what-is-the-mandela-effect-4589394">Mandela effect&lt;/a>-ed myself into believing that was the case), I&amp;rsquo;d heard of a Pomodoro timer before, but largely dismissed it as being silly. This book takes you on a journey through the power of human habit that is so illuminating and powerful that it convinced me to take on new strategies to combat my worst habit: distractibility. So sit down and shut up reader, because for the remaining ~18 minutes&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>, I&amp;rsquo;m going to be so fucking focused on reviewing this book you&amp;rsquo;re not going to believe it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Duhigg starts small in scope, showing us the habits of individual smokers, over-eaters, alcoholics who are now regularly jogging, eating salads, and excelling in their careers. The first three &lt;em>before&lt;/em> descriptions don&amp;rsquo;t quite match with the &lt;em>after&lt;/em> ones, and that&amp;rsquo;s part of the point. One of the first revelations in the book is that &lt;strong>changing&lt;/strong> one bad habit often cascades into other parts of your life. Duhigg first focuses on Lisa, a smoker who was suffering through a rough divorce, and makes a rash trip to Cairo, even more rashly vowing that she would return in a year to trek through an Egyptian desert. For that to be possible, she decided she would need to give up smoking.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>[&amp;hellip;] to the scientists at the laboratory, the details of her trek weren&amp;rsquo;t relevant. Because for reasons they were just beginning to understand, that one small shift in Lisa&amp;rsquo;s perception that day in Cairo—the conviction that she &lt;em>had&lt;/em> to give up smoking to accomplish her goal—had touched off a series of changes that would ultimately radiate out to every part of her life. Over the next six months, she would replace smoking with jogging, and that, in turn, changed how she ate, worked, slept, saved money, scheduled her workdays, planned for the future, and so on. [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It wasn&amp;rsquo;t the trip to Cairo that had caused the shift, scientists were convinced, or the divorce or desert trek. It was that Lisa had focused on changing just one habit—smoking—at first. [&amp;hellip;] By focusing on one pattern—what is known as a &amp;ldquo;keystone habit&amp;rdquo;—Lisa had taught herself how to reprogram the other routines in her life, as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Keystone habits pop up a lot in this book, I&amp;rsquo;d call them, and &amp;ldquo;The Habit Loop&amp;rdquo;, the main characters, and probably what you should focus on if you&amp;rsquo;re hoping to use this book to change your own habits&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;img src="https://kalverra.github.io/images/review-the-power-of-habit/the-habit-loop.png" alt="the habit loop">
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Duhigg quickly establishes this loop and its power through a few studies (including the curious case of &lt;a href="https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2013/04/130422154947.htm">Eugene Pauly&lt;/a>, who suffered severe brain damage, leaving only his habitual mind) and applies it to each story in the book. The book is mostly stories and anecdotes from the subjects of these academic studies on habits. The structure is nicely done to stop the book from being too dry, using individual stories is effective for keeping my attention and getting your point across in concrete ways. But you can quit it with the bullshit cliffhangers all over the place. At least once a chapter Duhigg builds the story up to a point of &amp;ldquo;and you&amp;rsquo;ll never guess what happens next&amp;rdquo; then do a line break and jump back in the storyline, or sometimes to a totally different one. It&amp;rsquo;s not a large complaint, but it baffled me every time that this man is telling me to tune in next week so I can catch the thrilling conclusion to how Starbucks works.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The book is split into 3 parts, growing in scope as Duhigg explores habits in individuals, companies, and finally societies. This is where the more &amp;ldquo;academic&amp;rdquo; aspects of the book come in, and where I think it gets its most interesting, but also less useful for a distracted engineer to immediately incorporate in his life.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="part-1-habits-of-individuals" >Part 1: Habits of Individuals
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#part-1-habits-of-individuals">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Habits are hard to manufacture, that&amp;rsquo;s basically the entirety of LA Fitness&amp;rsquo;s business model. Get you to buy a membership intending to build this new, healthy habit, then make it impossible to cancel the thing when you inevitably don&amp;rsquo;t actually go with a combination of shame and bureaucratic bullshittery. It&amp;rsquo;s tricky because habits are built in pursuit of a reward, and if you don&amp;rsquo;t find an obvious reward at the end of that treadmill, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to keep up, and if for whatever reason your brain isn&amp;rsquo;t coded to accept that exercise endorphin rush as a good thing, then you&amp;rsquo;ve got to employ other strategies. For this reason only one chapter is spent on creating new habits, while most others are focused on changing existing ones.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Habits aren&amp;rsquo;t destiny. [&amp;hellip;] habits can be ignored, changed, or replaced. But the reason the discovery of the habit loop is so important is that it reveals a basic truth: When a habit emerges, the brain stops fully participating in decision making. It stops working so hard, or diverts focus to other tasks. So unless you deliberately &lt;em>fight&lt;/em> a habit—unless you find new routines—the pattern will unfold automatically.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, simply understanding how habits work—learning the structure of the habit loop—makes them easier to control. Once you break a habit into its components, you can fiddle with the gears.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The power of habit is that our brains run a program in the background to save its energy when certain conditions are met. And if you can modify the program, you can train your brain in some useful ways. As a programmer this is a fascinating revelation, that my brain is running &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cron">cron jobs&lt;/a> all the time, and with a little work I can tweak the commands being run. But I can never delete them. This seems accepted a priori in the book, that habits are near impossible to fully delete. Duhigg writes, if you&amp;rsquo;ve &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_Pavlov">Pavlov&lt;/a>-ed&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> yourself into drinking a beer every time the football game is on, you&amp;rsquo;ll find it incredibly difficult to stop and just drink nothing. Your cue (football game), routine (get a beer), and reward (taste and sweet oblivion) have been indelibly established. You&amp;rsquo;ll have much better luck tweaking the routine part&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> of that habit loop, so reaching for a seltzer water or non-alcoholic beer instead will greatly increase your chances of changing your routine. The difficult part here is stopping your brain from shutting off. You have to be vigilant to recognize the habit and each part of the loop that is in play. When you&amp;rsquo;ve done that, you then have to stop your brain from going with its usual behavior and shift it to the new one.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I get the sense that Duhigg isn&amp;rsquo;t a big drinker, smoker, or recreational drug user of any kind. The book has little lip service paid to the unending difficulties of uprooting bad habits like addictive drugs, lip service that most current and former drug aficionados cannot resist opining on. Although he brings up examples of people quitting smoking and drinking utilizing these habit-modification techniques (there&amp;rsquo;s quite a few mentions of Alcoholics Anonymous), there&amp;rsquo;s little said about chemical addiction. It seems to me that chemical addiction would be something like habit formation in overdrive, or it maybe reinforces the reward part of the loop so deeply that nothing else can emulate it. Though he does acknowledge this is all easier said than done.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>It is important to note that though the process of habit change is easily described, it does not necessarily follow that it is easily accomplished. It is facile to imply that smoking, alcoholism, overeating, or other ingrained patterns can be upended without real effort. Genuine change requires work and self-understanding of the cravings driving behaviors. Changing any habit requires determination. No one will quit smoking cigarettes simply because they sketch a habit loop.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="part-2-habits-of-companies" >Part 2: Habits of Companies
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#part-2-habits-of-companies">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Keystone habits pop up occasionally when Duhigg talks about individuals, but they really come into play for corporate habits. I think because a corporation is a much bigger beast than an individual, so if you&amp;rsquo;re looking to change any habits, there&amp;rsquo;s mountains more friction in your way, so picking a single habit that can have far-reaching consequences if far preferable. He opens this section by exploring the newly appointed CEO of the Aluminum Company of America (Alcoa), Paul O&amp;rsquo;Neill. O&amp;rsquo;Neill sought to turn around the flailing company by doing something no 1980s business man could dream of: make the workplace safer.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>O&amp;rsquo;Neill believed that some habits have the power to start a chain reaction, changing other habits as they move through an organization. Some habits, in other words, matter more than others in remaking businesses and lives. These are &amp;ldquo;keystone habits,&amp;rdquo; and they can influence how people work, eat, play, live, spend, and communicate. Keystone habits start a process that, over time, transforms everything.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>O&amp;rsquo;Neill identified factory safety as the keystone habit to change, and he really fucking cared about it. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t some bullshit pandering that bigwigs said to quiet the rabble, he bought better machines, implemented new standards, and fired an effective executive when that exec was slow to report an incident in accordance with O&amp;rsquo;Neill&amp;rsquo;s new standards. Before O&amp;rsquo;Neill, the company was getting wrecked by competitors, and everyone assumed this focus on safety would slow down Alcoa even more. His investors balked in classic 1980s businessman fashion: &amp;ldquo;Profit is driven by children&amp;rsquo;s faces covered in coal dust! Asbestos filled machines with every surface sharpened to a razor&amp;rsquo;s edge! If I so much as hear about an emergency shutoff I&amp;rsquo;m going to fill the room with chainsaws!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But O&amp;rsquo;Neill kept at it, the safety records meaningfully improved, as did the rest of the company. It turns out safety was a keystone habit and improving it triggered a slew of other improvements. The newer machines were safer, they also jammed less and made better products. Workers trusted management more, management trusted workers more, and overall productivity soared.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>If you focus on changing or cultivating keystone habits, you can cause widespread shifts. However, identifying keystone habits is tricky. To find them, you have to know where to look. Detecting keystone habits means searching out certain characteristics. Keystone habits offer what is known within academic literature as &amp;ldquo;small wins.&amp;rdquo; They help other habits to flourish by creating new structures, and they establish cultures where change becomes contagious.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The &amp;ldquo;if you know where to look&amp;rdquo; part is the rub here, as not much direction is given in that aspect. Though just observationally through some of the book&amp;rsquo;s examples, the answer tends to be something innocuous that also touches many aspects of the whole process&lt;sup id="fnref:5">&lt;a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. If you can change that, so much more can change as well. For individuals, a common one is exercise, but I&amp;rsquo;m unsure if companies share any common ones to focus on.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The other big example Duhigg uses isn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily the habit of a company, but rather how companies have independently discovered the powers of habit, and effectively exploit them to a creepy degree. He details the story of Target&amp;rsquo;s data scientists who were able to spot when people were pregnant, sometimes even before the mothers themselves knew. Target would track purchase histories, and found out that newly-pregnant women bought at each stage of pregnancy, and would send them coupons for those items. New mothers found this creepy as shit&lt;sup id="fnref:6">&lt;a href="#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">6&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>, so Target learned to get sneaky with it. You&amp;rsquo;d get a coupon booklet for a bunch of stuff, plus a couple of totally-not-targeted stroller and diaper discounts.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="part-3-habits-of-societies" >Part 3: Habits of Societies
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#part-3-habits-of-societies">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>This section has me conflicted. I simultaneously believe Duhigg is reaching too far, but maybe has a point. The big focus is the &lt;a href="https://kinginstitute.stanford.edu/montgomery-bus-boycott">Montgomery bus boycott&lt;/a> that Rosa Parks kicked off, and launched MLK. Duhigg&amp;rsquo;s argument is that anti-black discrimination in Montgomery was habitual. The exchange between Rosa Parks and the cop who arrested her bolsters this (and is also pretty gangster shit from Rosa Parks).&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;If you don&amp;rsquo;t stand up,&amp;rdquo; [the bus driver] said, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m going to call the police and have you arrested.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;You may do that,&amp;rdquo; Parks said.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The driver left and found two policemen.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Why don&amp;rsquo;t you stand up?&amp;rdquo; one of them asked Parks after they boarded.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Why do you push us around?&amp;rdquo; she said&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know,&amp;rdquo; the officer answered. &amp;ldquo;But the law is the law and you&amp;rsquo;re under arrest.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;You may do that&amp;rdquo; is a fantastic, movie-worthy line, and so is the officer saying &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know&amp;rdquo;. It perfectly encapsulates Duhigg&amp;rsquo;s point that this discrimination had fallen into the habit loop where white people didn&amp;rsquo;t even think about their behavior, their brains went on auto-pilot and discriminated because it was the easy thing to do, and black people withstood the abuse because they had adopted a habit to do so.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A lot has been said about why specifically Parks was the one to spark this revolution, she wasn&amp;rsquo;t the first black person to refuse to give up her seat on the bus, but she was a beloved community figure who was involved with a lot of tight-knit communities in the area, so she was easy to rally around. There were a lot of social science phenomena going on during the Montgomery bus boycotts, but I&amp;rsquo;m not fully convinced that habits were a part of it. Duhigg asserts that habits of friendship and social interaction dictate a lot of what happened in Montgomery.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Movements don&amp;rsquo;t emerge because everyone suddenly decides to face the same direction at once. They rely on social patterns that begin as the habits of friendship, grow through the habits of communities, and are sustained by new habits that change participants&amp;rsquo; sense of self.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I still think Duhigg is doing some round-peg-square-hole work here. Habits are powerful forces in our lives, as he&amp;rsquo;s proved in previous chapters, but was it adherence to habits that kept protestors in the streets? Or was it the power of the ideals they were fighting for, and the extraordinarily charismatic leader in MLK that kept them going? I&amp;rsquo;d wager the latter as a more powerful force in compelling behavior on this sort of scale.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-freewill-thing" >The Freewill Thing
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#the-freewill-thing">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Habits are a powerful and fundamental force of the human mind. We quite literally stop thinking and assessing our actions for moments of time to get our reward. So are we a slave to the habits? Are we simply collections of cron jobs running all day? And are we responsible for their consequences?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So much of my own time has been spent on pushing this freewill thought around in circles I kind of checked out for this section. I think freewill is the ultimate &lt;a href="https://xkcd.com/356/">nerd-snipe&lt;/a> for the philosophically minded, and until we can get some sort of smoking gun, we&amp;rsquo;re going nowhere. And habits are not that smoking gun. Duhigg clearly shows that with a little work, we can modify and interrupt habits. Maybe you lose autonomy for a little bit, but you can recognize and fight it with the proper willpower, strategy, and assistance.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="key-takeaways" >Key Takeaways
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#key-takeaways">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The habit loop is powerful, and shuts your brain off to save energy. Knowing this enables you to recognize the loop and modify it, which is generally the best way to approach things as habits are hard to manufacture, but relatively easy to change.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Habits are near impossible to completely delete without some surgery or copious amounts of booze.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Recognizing the habit is the first step, then the hard work of actually changing it begins.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>How to Modify the Habit&lt;/strong>: nail down the loop and you can change it. The loop components can be hard to spot.
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Identify the routine: figure out what habits you have&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Experiment with rewards: figure out what exactly the reward is, try new ones, see if you&amp;rsquo;re satisfied&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Isolate the cue: we&amp;rsquo;re bombarded with info and events, you need the exact thing that triggers your habit&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Have a plan: devise a specific plan that modifies the habit and execute it dutifully&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>This took far more time and timer session to finish than I anticipated. I had a draft where I included whenever I finished a session, but discarded that bit as it added little more than clutter. Albeit it&amp;rsquo;s an effective tool, enough that I already resisted trying to build my own program to do it, and bought my lifetime subscription to &lt;a href="https://pomofocus.io/app">Pomofocus&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>As I imagine 99% of people who read this book are.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3">
&lt;p>Pavlov is not mentioned in this book at all. Not a single reference. I figure his work is probably wildly out of date at this point, and I can imagine anyone &lt;a href="https://www.iflscience.com/pavlov-s-dog-experiment-was-much-more-disturbing-than-you-think-65729">who loves dogs would probably not want to acknowledge his existence&lt;/a>, but still, seems like an odd exclusion.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4">
&lt;p>I guess you could also eliminate the cue in this case, just never watch football. But that&amp;rsquo;s probably a non-starter for most.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:5">
&lt;p>Side rant: I think focusing on eliminating automated test flakes would be a great candidate for this in a software company. Flakes are often frustrating, but accepted matter-of-fact and people just re-run the test. I think prioritizing eliminating flakey tests can bring a massive amount of organizational focus to bear on overall product quality. Less bugs and crashes, more focus on building maintainable and testable code, and less likelihood to ship broken shit.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:6">
&lt;p>This is maybe showing the age of the book, but this felt very much like Duhigg was trying to shock me with the revelation that &amp;ldquo;corporations track your behavior!&amp;rdquo;, and I could feel his mood fall as I told him &amp;ldquo;ya, no shit they do&amp;rdquo;. I was also hoping for more deep dive on exactly the math/programming that went into Target&amp;rsquo;s system at the time, but I left understandably disappointed.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Review: A Philosophy of Software Design</title><link>https://kalverra.github.io/books/review-a-philosophy-of-software-design/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kalverra.github.io/books/review-a-philosophy-of-software-design/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/39996759">A Philosophy of Software Design by John Ousterhout&lt;/a> is a wide ranging, highly opinionated look at general software design practices and how to best implement them. It vacillates from big-picture musings on &amp;ldquo;The Nature of Complexity&amp;rdquo;, down to seemingly miniscule squabbles around &amp;ldquo;Choosing Names&amp;rdquo; for variables and methods.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-author" >The Author
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#the-author">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://web.stanford.edu/~ouster/cgi-bin/home.php">John Ousterhout&lt;/a> is a computer scientist who got his PhD from Carnegie Mellon, did some cool research work, bounced around the industry a bit, and has settled back into academia as a faculty member at Stanford where he regularly teaches courses on software design. He claims teaching this course is what gave him most of his inspiration and material in writing the book. He also thanks a group of people for their help in the book, including &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rob_Pike">Rob Pike&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.jameskoppel.com/">James Koppel&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-book" >The Book
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#the-book">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Broken down into highly structured and compact chapters, Ousterhout touches on what he considers the most crucial considerations for writing modern software. He starts out by ultimately declaring complexity to be an enemy of the state of software, and anytime you find yourself writing complex code, you need to take a good look at what has led you down this demonic path.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The most fundamental problem in computer science is problem decomposition: how to take a complex problem and divide it up into pieces that can be solved independently [&amp;hellip;] we must find ways to make software simpler. Complexity will still increase over time, in spite of our best efforts, but simpler designs allow us to build larger and more powerful systems before complexity becomes overwhelming.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This problem remains prevalent no matter how much sheer willpower we have thrown at it as an industry. It seems that CS is often the &lt;em>practice&lt;/em> of independent problem solving, rather than its antagonist. Framing this as a &amp;ldquo;problem&amp;rdquo; strikes me as odd in the same way if someone told me that &amp;lsquo;math would be perfect if it weren&amp;rsquo;t for all these pesky equations&amp;rsquo;. I&amp;rsquo;m getting bogged down in semantics here, the ultimate idea is that intertwined systems lead to complexity, and complexity ultimately leads to bugs, frustration, and screaming at my computer like a lunatic when it keeps printing &lt;code>a&lt;/code> despite me &lt;em>clearly&lt;/em> telling it to print &lt;code>b&lt;/code>. Ousterhout spends the rest of the book detailing what he means by complexity, then delving into the strategies to avoid it. Each chapter details one of these strategies, providing a handy summary at the end of each one, and some red flags to watch for when you can likely implement a specific strategy to remove complexity from your design.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Every rule has its exceptions, and every principle has its limits. If you take any design idea to its extreme, you will probably end up in a bad place. Beautiful designs reflect a balance between competing ideas and approaches.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The book is staunchly opinionated on design approaches, what types of problems to focus on, and how to fix them. But it consistently warns that taking any solution to the extreme will ultimately lead you back into the clutches of complexity. And what exactly is complexity?&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Complexity is anything related to the structure of a software system that makes it hard to understand and modify the system. Complexity can take many forms. For example, it might be hard to understand how a piece of code works; it might take a lot of effort to implement a small improvement, or it might not be clear which parts of the system must be modified to make the improvement&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first symptom of complexity is that a seemingly simple change requires code modifications in many different places.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The second symptom of complexity is cognitive load, which refers to how much a developer needs to know in order to complete a task.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The third symptom of complexity is that it is not obvious which pieces of code must be modified to complete a task, or what information a developer must have to carry out the task successfully.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Of the three manifestations of complexity, unknown unknowns are the worst. An unknown unknown means that there is something you need to know, but there is no way for you to find out what it is, or even whether there is an issue.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Complexity itself is defined rather amorphously; it&amp;rsquo;s largely left to &amp;ldquo;you know it when you see it&amp;rdquo;. Which is fine for me. I&amp;rsquo;ve rarely found myself disagreeing with someone about whether some code is complex or not. Conflict usually begins when we start asking pesky questions like &amp;ldquo;how do we make it simpler?&amp;rdquo;. This question is what Ousterhout spends the majority of the book answering.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I won&amp;rsquo;t detail all of his suggestions here (take a look at the Table of Contents for a good idea), but I found his focus on comments and naming (5 of the 22 chapters) intriguing, mostly because I&amp;rsquo;ve found myself to be more focused on this aspect than nearly all of my colleagues, and often took that focus as a sign of me being somehow inferior as a programmer; that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t magically divine what the code is doing showed that I was somehow deficient. It turns out that Ousterhout agrees with me that this is something to focus heavily on, and can really help everyone. Some of his advice includes &lt;strong>starting your method by writing the comment&lt;/strong> then work on the implementation, taking care to update the comments as you make changes to the original design. This can be annoying — especially as you make lots of changes in need of documenting — but forces you to at least write &lt;em>something&lt;/em>, where most people never bother going that far.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My only real criticism of the book is the same I have for all programming books: its reliance on toy problems. Toy problems are a necessity for this stuff. You can&amp;rsquo;t just say &amp;ldquo;my example is Kubernetes, go read it&amp;rdquo;, I need digestible problems to learn your lessons from. For the concrete problems and solutions Ousterhout focuses on, this use of toy problems makes even more sense, but so often I find that simplifying the issue often trivializes the solution. So applying some of the toy code advice to a situation where I actually am working on code as large and complex as Kubernetes becomes tricky.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can see this in another light though, as Ousterhout continually mentions that the complexity we most often encounter is rarely a symptom of overall design, but rather is added in small increments over the years, until you find yourself staring at a 50 layer &lt;code>if-else&lt;/code> garbage pile. Just like no one looks like Arnold Schwarzenegger after a couple days in the gym, and Schwarzenegger doesn&amp;rsquo;t gain 50 pounds of fat after eating a bag of chips, these large transitions usually take time. It&amp;rsquo;s those little decisions, like choosing to comment your code, spend a little more investment on a simpler design, focusing on more-frequent use cases on that one method, those little acts of care add up to reduce overall complexity as long as you consistently adhere to their underlying philosophy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-takeaways" >The Takeaways
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#the-takeaways">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>The book is excellent. I found myself silently nodding to myself as I read over written forms of lessons I had long ago internalized in my experience of writing software. I wish I had read it sooner, and I think that if you&amp;rsquo;re a college senior embarking on your career — or have been working for a few years — this book is ideal. Here&amp;rsquo;s a scattering of key quotes and takeaways I felt to be poignant.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>it’s worth taking a little extra time to find a simple design for each new class; rather than implementing the first idea that comes to mind, try a couple of alternative designs and pick the cleanest one. Try to imagine a few ways in which the system might need to be changed in the future and make sure that will be easy with your design.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I find this can sometimes paralyze me with decision paralysis though. Best to not be taken to the extreme.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>interfaces should be designed to make the common case as simple as possible&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>An opinionated book recommends you use an opinionated design. Though sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s tricky to predict just how exactly people will use your code.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Information leakage is one of the most important red flags in software design. One of the best skills you can learn as a software designer is a high level of sensitivity to information leakage. If you encounter information leakage between classes, ask yourself “How can I reorganize these classes so that this particular piece of knowledge only affects a single class?”&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>I have found over and over that specialization leads to complexity; I now think that over-specialization may be the single greatest cause of complexity in software. Conversely, code that is more general-purpose is simpler, cleaner, and easier to understand.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>I have noticed that the design-it-twice principle is sometimes hard for really smart people to embrace. When they are growing up, smart people discover that their first quick idea about any problem is sufficient for a good grade; there is no need to consider a second or third possibility. This tends to result in bad work habits. However, as these people get older, they get promoted into environments with harder and harder problems. Eventually, everyone reaches a point where your first ideas are no longer good enough; if you want to get really great results, you have to consider a second possibility, or perhaps a third, no matter how smart you are. The design of large software systems falls in this category: no-one is good enough to get it right with their first try.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>If you want to maintain a clean design for a system, you must take a strategic approach when modifying existing code. Ideally, when you have finished with each change, the system will have the structure it would have had if you had designed it from the start with that change in mind.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I love this idea, but it&amp;rsquo;s hard to focus on when this change is blocking 5 different teams that need it now.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Don’t change existing conventions. Resist the urge to “improve” on existing conventions. Having a “better idea” is not a sufficient excuse to introduce inconsistencies. Your new idea may indeed be better, but the value of consistency over inconsistency is almost always greater than the value of one approach over another.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Consistency == Readability&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Programmers’ intuitions about performance are unreliable. This is true even for experienced developers. If you start making changes based on intuition, you’ll waste time on things that don’t actually improve performance, and you’ll probably make the system more complicated in the process.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Design it, then measure it to find out where you fucked up.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>