<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Essays on Adam's Writing Thing</title><link>https://kalverra.github.io/essays/</link><description>Adam's Writing Thing (Essays)</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kalverra.github.io/essays/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Do I Have ADHD?</title><link>https://kalverra.github.io/essays/do-i-have-adhd/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kalverra.github.io/essays/do-i-have-adhd/</guid><description>&lt;p>At this point, I’m pretty positive I do, but I’m still not fully convinced, and I’m still not entirely sure why I’m not entirely sure yet. Maybe this essay exists solely for my own benefit of organizing my thoughts and feelings on the matter, or maybe someone else will find this enlightening as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was recently diagnosed with ADHD by a psychiatrist and my primary care doctor who concurred. I’m 28 years old and was never flagged as ADHD before, but I suspect that is largely because I was in environments that were maybe not the best at recognizing or even acknowledging the existence of ADHD. Here are some myth-busting and baseline premises I’ve discovered as part of this process.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>ADHD is a real thing that affects how your brain works. It has been &lt;a href="https://www.additudemag.com/brain-mri-scans-adhd-research/">picked up in brain scans&lt;/a> (though &lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7879851/">it’s not fully settled on how that works yet&lt;/a>), and we can reliably diagnose it by looking at the repeated behaviors of those who have it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It is commonly diagnosed in children but can be discovered and diagnosed in adults. (There are some rumblings of &lt;a href="https://add.org/can-adhd-appear-for-the-first-time-in-adulthood/">adult-onset ADHD being a thing&lt;/a>, but most people think it’s adults that never got diagnosed.)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The concept of ADHD has been around since &lt;a href="https://www.notion.so/Therapy-and-ADHD-b0935a99286841ab8c0800ff234760bc?pvs=21">the early 1900s&lt;/a>. There are some theories that our current environment of overwhelming technology has contributed to its existence (I’m currently surrounded by four computer monitors and a cell phone, all buzzing notifications at me), but there’s no definitive word on that yet, and it’s certainly not the only cause.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.cdc.gov/ncbddd/adhd/data.html">About 13% of U.S. boys are diagnosed&lt;/a>, and 6% of girls. However, there is &lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8042533/">some agreement that we’ve been a bit too trigger-happy with that diagnosis&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It is genetic. If one of your parents has it, there’s a &lt;a href="https://www.notion.so/Therapy-and-ADHD-b0935a99286841ab8c0800ff234760bc?pvs=21">roughly 35% chance you do&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There are a few different treatment approaches, but behavioral interventions (&lt;a href="https://todoist.com/productivity-methods/pomodoro-technique">Pomodoro timers&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://todoist.com/productivity-methods/getting-things-done">GTD method&lt;/a>) + stimulant medications (Adderall, Vyvanse, etc) seem to be by far the most effective.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>“Adderall/Vyvanse/Whatever is just giving kids meth” is… well &lt;a href="https://www.astralcodexten.com/p/know-your-amphetamines">kind of true&lt;/a>. Though there’s a massive difference between taking a dose or two of highly controlled and regulated Adderall in the morning and shoving crystal meth up your butt for 3 days straight, they’re chemically very similar.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-it" >What Is It?
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#what-is-it">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>There are plenty of better resources on this; I particularly liked &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hFL6qRIJZ_Y">this Andrew Huberman podcast&lt;/a> on the matter (his &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2024/mar/28/podcaster-andrew-huberman-goop-for-bros">recent controversy&lt;/a> and weird following aside, the content seems solid).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I best understood it as a computer metaphor. A brain’s default process looks for information all around it, noticing everything it can. When it finds an idea or a sensation it wants to focus on, it quiets this primary process and gives way to a focused process that can shut out the noise around it and dive deep into that area for a limited amount of time. When that focus process is finished, or runs out of energy to continue, the primary process re-asserts itself and starts looking for something new to focus on. Occasionally there’s a bug or misunderstanding, and the primary and focus processes get out of sync. They both try to run at the same time or not at all. So while you’re trying to read a book or finish something at work, a million other things are going through your mind. Or your brain feels so blocked and empty that your only desire is to lay motionless in a dark room. This is an annoying occurrence for neurotypical people, but is a way of life for ADHD people. Also it’s suspected ADHD people have &lt;a href="https://www.thinkkids.com/blog/how-adhd-contributes-to-memory-problems">less RAM&lt;/a> than most others.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-do-i-think-i-have-it" >Why Do I Think I Have It?
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#why-do-i-think-i-have-it">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Mostly because multiple doctors, after listening to my issues and having me take &lt;a href="https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/adhd-questionnaire-ASRS111.pdf">this survey&lt;/a>, said I do. Also, the more I learn about &lt;a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/adult-adhd/symptoms-causes/syc-20350878">common symptoms&lt;/a> and listen to the stories of others with ADHD, all of these things match my experience to an uncanny degree. Some that match with me particularly:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Easily overwhelmed when faced with what most would consider a reasonable task list.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Extreme difficulty concentrating on any one thing, even things I enjoy like TV, books, and video games. It’s easy to feel restless and reach out for the next thing, and the internet is an especially dangerous tool to have here. I’ll start something at work I’m excited about, then some other random thought will enter my mind, and in no time, the day will be done. I’ll be watching two videos in the background about system design while reading some esoteric article on poisonous frogs. Even as I write this, I’ve switched my attention to a bunch of random, unconnected topics. I’ve also jumped around the essay itself, writing a couple sentences in one spot and then jumping halfway down the page to elaborate on some other point.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Except sometimes when my brain decides something is unbelievably fascinating, so much so that I’ll forget to shower or eat because I need to know every detail about how dogs’ noses work. Most people refer to this as &lt;a href="https://add.org/adhd-hyperfocus/">hyperfocus&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Hearing the phrase “wasted potential” a lot as a kid.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Constantly forgetting appointments, where I put my keys, how to get home, and the names of people I’ve known for weeks.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I can never seem to finish anything. My history is littered with assignments, hobbies, and projects that all are close to the finish line, but never made it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I have a hard time getting to sleep because I’m always thinking of &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/ADHD_Programmers/top/">random bullshit that I need to know about NOW&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I’m constantly fidgeting with something, getting up to pace, or generally being restless.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I have multiple relatives, including both my mother and grandmother, who have either official diagnoses or match a lot of the above symptoms.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I was recently prescribed Adderall, and it was such an emotional experience I cried with joy at the end of the day, a reaction that is nearly ubiquitous among ADHD people and not all that common among others.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>When listing these symptoms, it’s common for people to say things like, “I forget my keys and get distracted sometimes too. That doesn’t mean I’m ADHD,” to which you’d be right. Human brains are all broadly similar. We all get sad, distracted, and prideful sometimes. But there’s a difference between experiencing something occasionally and experiencing something almost always. Everyone gets sad, but not everyone is depressed. Everyone gets distracted, but not everyone has ADHD. Everyone has moments of pride, but not everyone is a narcissist. But when these things happen every day, so much so that your wife is frequently mad at you because of your inability to remember plans or appointments; or you need to designate a specific place in your house where your keys and wallet go, otherwise you will lose countless time every day looking for them, you’ve established a pattern of behavior that indicates your brain works differently than others.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-am-i-not-fully-convinced-i-do" >Why Am I Not Fully Convinced I Do?
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#why-am-i-not-fully-convinced-i-do">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>I still hold this doubt in the back of my mind, so I will lay down my primary reasons for doubting and then try to debunk them because I’m more willing to believe multiple medical professionals on this matter than my own, uneducated doubts.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="its-statistically-unlikely" >It’s Statistically Unlikely
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#its-statistically-unlikely">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>This is the easiest to knock down. Even if we over-diagnose ADHD in the U.S., it’s still not a tiny probability. The lowest estimate I could find for ADHD &lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7916320/">occurrence in my demographic was 6.76%&lt;/a>, which is a slightly higher chance than rolling a one on a d20 die. If you’ve played enough Dungeons and Dragons, you know from personal experience that those odds are small, but they’re sure as shit not impossible.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="i-dont-match-all-of-the-symptoms" >I Don’t Match All of the Symptoms
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#i-dont-match-all-of-the-symptoms">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>ADHD is most commonly diagnosed in elementary or middle school. The stereotypical ADHD kid is always hyper-energy, can never sit still, is always getting in trouble, and has abysmal grades. A lot of adult ADHD sufferers also deal with impulsiveness and its consequences, like terrible credit scores, gambling debt, or an inordinately high amount of jobs and relationships.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was never a troublemaker as a kid, and while my grades were never spectacular, I typically excelled in English and History while underperforming in almost everything else. No one ever flagged me as ADHD when I was a kid&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. As an adult, I’ve made a few impulsive decisions here and there, but am relatively boring.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is all true, but it ignores the fact that a diagnosis of something does not require the presence of every single symptom. I’ve undeniably had COVID-19 at least three times. I displayed a lot of symptoms, but I never felt one of the most common COVID symptoms: a shortage of breath. That doesn’t mean I never had COVID; I have multiple tests to disprove that assumption.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="i-could-be-fooling-myself" >I Could Be Fooling Myself
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#i-could-be-fooling-myself">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>There is a psychological phenomenon called the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barnum_effect">Forer Effect&lt;/a> that I’m afraid of falling into. It’s a tendency for people to interpret very general statements about the human experience as having deep personal insight into themselves. Statements like “You have a tendency to be critical of yourself” and “You have a great need for other people to like and admire you” are general enough they apply to everyone, but when you hear them it’s common to think it describes you in particular and feel a deep emotional reaction. It’s how psychics and mind readers &lt;a href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/1224176/psychic-services-market-size-us/">make so much money&lt;/a> tricking you into thinking they have a particularly deep insight into your pysche.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But ADHD symptoms don’t seem to have that quality. There are some that are pretty general like, “You often feel overwhelmed when a lot is expected of you at once”, but others that are much more specific like, “You find it incredibly difficult to finish a task, even if the hardest parts are already done” or “You often feel overly active and compelled to do things, like you were driven by a motor.”&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-is-it-a-problem" >Why Is It a Problem?
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#why-is-it-a-problem">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Alright, I have it. Why is it something worth fixing?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_dUNWW2D3BM">This Ken Robinson talk&lt;/a> about education and ADHD makes a good point about how we see ADHD as a problem not because our brains are built wrong, but because the education system is. Society has been designed in overt and subtle ways to move all of humanity into some narrow pathways, pathways that don’t play to the strengths of ADHD people. While I can’t reform society, I can try finding a different niche within it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The problem is that I’m already in a niche considered nearly optimal for ADHD people. Being a software developer plays to many of ADHD’s strengths, where we can bounce around the walls learning 15 different things a day and then spend a week holed up doing nothing but hyper-focusing on a program. But it’s still an issue for me. My focus is scattered and unpredictable. It’s preventing me from where I want to go in my life and career, and it’s been something both my teammates and I have been frustrated with.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It also makes me anxious and &lt;a href="./working-through-depression.md">depressed consistently&lt;/a>. I always end the day tired because I was “working” all day, but I get very little done. So I’m exhausted, disappointed with myself, depressed at how little progress I’m making, and anxious for the next day. It’s been an unpleasant way of existing, and I thought it was normal for so long. To find out that it’s not has been a revelation.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="how-do-i-fix-it" >How Do I Fix It?
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#how-do-i-fix-it">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>My main complaint is lack of focus, specifically lacking consistent and controlled focus. I’m blessed with a flexible schedule, but it’s not flexible enough to let me sit around all day and wait for inspiration. So I need to focus (hehe) on solving that aspect. Other parts of my ADHD have proven useful in my life and career, being able to swap between a ton of things with little friction has led me to some interesting learning experiences.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="the-usuals" >The Usuals
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#the-usuals">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>A good diet, consistent exercise, lots of sleep, and cutting out things like alcohol are table stakes when dealing with pretty much any human issue. No matter who you are, if you don’t have these things together, you’re sabotaging any other solutions you come up with.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="pharmaceuticals" >Pharmaceuticals
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#pharmaceuticals">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Aside from the basics, good old-fashioned American drugs are the most effective way to treat ADHD. In children, they can even help change the structure of your brain over time so that ADHD doesn’t really bother you in adulthood anymore, which is badass. But for those of us who missed that boat, drugs are pretty much unavoidable for the rest of our lives.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are some non-stimulant medications you can take to help improve ADHD symptoms. &lt;a href="https://www.additudemag.com/wellbutrin-for-adhd/">Wellbutrin&lt;/a> is a depression medication that’s handy for this. It can also help with anxiety and depression, which tend to come packaged with ADHD. It didn’t do much for me, though.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://www.cdc.gov/ncbddd/adhd/treatment.html">obvious gotos&lt;/a> after that are &lt;a href="https://www.astralcodexten.com/p/know-your-amphetamines">amphetamines like Adderall and Vyvanse&lt;/a>. There’s a litany of different kinds, but they all do the same thing. For me, my first time on Adderall was a revelation akin to taking LSD for the first time. For the first time in my life, my brain was quiet. I didn’t get distracted all day by random bullshit, and at the end of the day, I was pleased. I finished a task from start to end, multiple tasks even! A feat that on a typical day seems impossible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are some risks to &lt;a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/12/28/adderall-risks-much-more-than-you-wanted-to-know/">using Adderall&lt;/a>. Dependency is the one I’m most concerned with. I’m still confused about what “addiction” means in this context. From Scott Alexander:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The data on this are really poor because it’s hard to define addiction. If a prescription stimulant user uses their stimulants every day, and feels really good on them, and feels really upset if they can’t get them…well, that’s basically the expected outcome.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I’ve heard anecdotally about people who become so dependent on Adderall that they become depressed zombies for long periods when they lose access to it. Given that amphetamine shortages &lt;a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/health/health-news/adhd-drug-shortage-adderall-ritalin-focalin-vyvanse-rcna137356">aren’t exactly rare events&lt;/a>, this is a real issue to consider. However, these stories tend to involve individuals with severe cases of ADHD. Before Adderall, they had so many issues in their interpersonal and professional lives that the possibility of dependence is more than worth the risk. Others can function fine if they miss a dose and regularly skip doses on weekends and vacations. I’m still new to this game but have found this strategy to be the best approach for me so far.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure>
&lt;img src="https://kalverra.github.io/images/do-i-have-adhd/focus_hours.png" alt="My tracked focus hours at work. Guess what day I started taking Adderall">
&lt;figcaption>My tracked focus hours at work. Guess what day I started taking Adderall&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="behavioral-interventions" >Behavioral Interventions
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#behavioral-interventions">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>It’s important to note that drugs aren’t a panacea. They unlock your ability to concentrate, but if you let yourself you can easily lock into learning about freshwater sharks all day instead of that program you need to write. Thankfully I’ve been working on these for a while&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> and have a pretty good stable of mental and tech tools that work for me.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Using &lt;a href="https://todoist.com/">TODOist&lt;/a> to keep track of my work and personal life tasks. Its reminders and scheduling are crucial for me to be able to remember to do anything. It also lets me break down tasks into smaller bites to fight of the &lt;a href="https://www.adhdcentre.co.uk/strategies-to-reduce-adhd-overwhelm/">dreaded overwhelm&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Using &lt;a href="https://pomofocus.io/app">Pomofocus&lt;/a> for my Pomodoro timers.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Using &lt;a href="https://blocksite.co/">Blocksite&lt;/a> to stop myself from going into unproductive rabbit holes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Meditation and mindfulness are &lt;a href="https://www.additudemag.com/how-to-meditate-for-adhd-symptoms/">helpful for ADHD people&lt;/a>. It’s been very effective for me to recognize when my attention is drifting and guiding it back to the thing I need to focus on. It is also surprisingly difficult to do consistently, even for neurotypical people.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Aggressively silencing notifications. During a Pomodoro session, I’ll make sure to put my phone on DND and stash it somewhere I can’t see it. Then on Slack, I’ll set my status to “Focusing” and pause notifications.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/@HowtoADHD">How to ADHD YouTube channel&lt;/a> has a lot of strategies and tips for handling common ADHD hurdles, and it’s short-format, engaging videos that are ideal for, well, people with ADHD.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="supplements" >Supplements
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#supplements">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>These vary wildly in effectiveness and have all sorts of issues as they’re unregulated, and frequently a &lt;a href="https://www.fda.gov/consumers/health-fraud-scams/health-fraud-product-database">favorite of fraudsters&lt;/a> to separate fools and cash from each other. That said, there are some that have minor but demonstrated helpful effects:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8875377/">Caffeine&lt;/a> can almost function like a micro does of Adderall for some people.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6093191/">Creatine&lt;/a> can help working memory. I mostly take it for muscle growth, but it has some small benefits to cognitive tasks.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fish Oil, specifically &lt;a href="https://www.additudemag.com/adhd-omega-3-benefits/">Omega-3s&lt;/a>, is particularly beneficial. There are a lot of claims about its benefits for heart health, and can apparently help a lot in focus and hyperactivity.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.nccih.nih.gov/health/ashwagandha">Ashwagandha&lt;/a> is a bit niche but apparently effective at &lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3221068/">improving attention&lt;/a>. Though I personally haven’t seen much benefit.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6574559/">L-theanine&lt;/a> is usually combined with a stimulant like caffeine or Adderall to help attention. There’s some anecdotal evidence out there and a few studies with small sample sizes. I haven&amp;rsquo;t tried it myself, but it might be next on the list.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="what-i-take-away-from-writing-this" >What I Take Away from Writing This
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#what-i-take-away-from-writing-this">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Well, I have ADHD. I think I&amp;rsquo;m ready to accept that. This was informative mostly for my own psyche, but on the miniscule chance that someone actually finds this, perhaps it can help them figure it out like I did. If you&amp;rsquo;re in that position, I will say I wish I had tried the scarier sounding interventions like Adderall sooner. It was akin to wearing glasses for the first time, and not at all how I expected it to be. It&amp;rsquo;s also tempting to think that discovering and treating something like this will ultimately &amp;ldquo;fix&amp;rdquo; you. It won&amp;rsquo;t, but it will help a whole lot.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>This could easily be due to the environment I was in at the time. The intricacies of ADHD still weren’t well understood at the time, especially outside of medical professionals. I was also a part of a school that held ADHD diagnoses with some suspicion, and I got the general vibe that most people didn’t believe it was a real thing. I thought I was just lazy or stupid.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>Funnily enough, building these behavioral solutions contributed to my discovery process. I kept on looking for solutions to my issues with focus and feeling overwhelmed, and I kept getting results back from ADHD guides and gurus. Which always struck me as a good idea, “Oh, I bet ADHD people have &lt;strong>way&lt;/strong> worse issues with this. They probably know what works well!” Then it dawned on me that many of these experiences sound awfully familiar…&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Working Through Depression</title><link>https://kalverra.github.io/essays/working-through-depression/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kalverra.github.io/essays/working-through-depression/</guid><description>&lt;p>My brain broke again and I&amp;rsquo;m sad all the time. Depression and anxiety aren&amp;rsquo;t foreign concepts to me; before I ever identified them using those words, the feelings have burst over me ever since I was in Elementary school. With no discernable origin&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>, feelings of hopelessness and worthlessness accost my brain and leave it in some mental ditch. I can&amp;rsquo;t do much of anything without finding some sort of flaw in my actions, methodology, motivations, and execution. Anything I do or produce is bad and I should feel bad about it. This of course spirals to making me feel bad that I&amp;rsquo;m beating myself up this way, and gives me zero leeway to feel pride or accomplishment in anything I do&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;img src="https://kalverra.github.io/images/working-through-depression/feel_bad.png" alt="Zoidberg echoing my flawless logic">
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>How you get there and what it looks like is different for everyone, but the basic chemical feedback loop of hopelessness and worthlessness and not bothering trying things or enjoying things because what&amp;rsquo;s the point anyway, tends to be the same. This is of course infuriating because actively doing and enjoying things is pretty much the only way to work your way out of a depressive episode. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to feel hopeless and worthless when all you do is lay in bed all day doing nothing, so you just reinforce your &lt;a href="https://www.health.harvard.edu/blog/how-to-recognize-and-tame-your-cognitive-distortions-202205042738">cognitive distortions&lt;/a> and end up transforming them from distortions into realities.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Working past depression is hard, monotonous work. Convincing myself that I&amp;rsquo;m worthy of treatment in the first place is tricky&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. Therapy, medication, exercise, and celebrating my accomplishments all mean taking some amount of initiative to schedule an appointment, or drive to a gym, or do something in the first place, which to a person who views getting out from under the covers as an insurmountable challenge, these all are ludicrously difficult, not to mention what would be the point anyway? I can&amp;rsquo;t willpower depression away the same way I can&amp;rsquo;t just sheer effort myself better from the flu. But I can willpower myself towards the things that can help me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is where the title&amp;rsquo;s double-meaning kicks in: I still gotta work. Beating myself up while laying still in bed isn&amp;rsquo;t an option, I have to take the show on the road. Both to try and fix the issue, and to avoid even more issues. I&amp;rsquo;ve succumbed to the temptation to just bury my head in a pillow and eschew all responsibilities before, and the consequences can be immense. I nearly failed a couple classes in high school, which at the time felt like the end of the world&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>, but now I&amp;rsquo;m an honest-to-goodness adult, I have so many more opportunities to fuck up my life! I could lose my job, ruin relationships and opportunities while laying motionless, wondering what the point of it all is. So I&amp;rsquo;m still working, I&amp;rsquo;m still going to the gym, walking the dog, keeping the house clean, and trying to celebrate even the smallest of accomplishments. I just do it all through a haze, like I&amp;rsquo;m in some old allergy medicine commercial, walking through a beautiful field of flowers while frowning underneath a grey filter. Even now writing these words I&amp;rsquo;m frustrated at how cliche I sound, what a horrible writer I am, how no one will ever read this&lt;sup id="fnref:5">&lt;a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> and I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t even bother. But I&amp;rsquo;m gonna fucking write it and post it through sheer determination that I can pat myself on the back that I actually finished something, even if I think it&amp;rsquo;s trite garbage. And I&amp;rsquo;ll do it tomorrow, committing some code I think is bad, and it may or may not actually be bad, but I won&amp;rsquo;t ever admit I think it&amp;rsquo;s good because I made it, making it naturally inferior. But I committed it, so I at least got that far.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This process is exhausting from a willpower standpoint, so you have to be smart about where to invest it. I&amp;rsquo;m getting my work done, but the bed if often unmade, the laundry piles up, and I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten trigger-happy with ordering takeout for dinner. It&amp;rsquo;s also exhausting from the pure banality of the process. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to get lost in the monotony of life on a good day, but when your brain has decided that it&amp;rsquo;s all going to be boring and unsatisfying no matter what, it&amp;rsquo;s suffocating. It&amp;rsquo;s made even worse knowing that there is no real end-game here. My prize is that I keep on living life, but with more flavor. I don&amp;rsquo;t reach some magical epiphany and ascend into Nirvana, I don&amp;rsquo;t even find an excitingly new answer. I know the answer, I beat myself up too much. I need to be kinder to myself. But telling me that is as good as telling someone with an eating disorder that they need to just eat differently. Or telling an alcoholic that alcohol is unhealthy. No shit. But you have to keep reminding yourself every minute of that same, uninspiring and uncomplicated answer to make any progress. And it never stops being annoying. The road to recovery is paved with tired platitudes, and sports a million billboards of infuriatingly obvious motivational posters.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>This is an annoying wrinkle to the whole ordeal. There&amp;rsquo;s rarely a definitive cause to these feelings. While a tragic event, or other life stressors certainly can kick off the chemical cascade, for me it&amp;rsquo;s rarely the case. The feelings pummel me at random. I often wish I could identify some definitive cause, as if I could shout &amp;ldquo;Eureka!&amp;rdquo; at it and have all my emotional issues immediately solved, &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/ZQht2yOX9Js?si=5cXyfCkKqoU7wnp0">Good Will Hunting style&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>An example of such thinking recently when writing some code: &amp;ldquo;This code is garbage, why can&amp;rsquo;t I write anything good? Will anyone actually use this or care? I hope not, if anyone sees this they&amp;rsquo;ll realize how bad I am at programming. Oh look, a bug, I should have thought of that before. I&amp;rsquo;m so stupid. Why am I being so hard on myself? I need to stop doing that, I&amp;rsquo;m my own worst enemy, it&amp;rsquo;s why I&amp;rsquo;ll never succeed in life. My boss said I&amp;rsquo;m doing well, but he&amp;rsquo;s just lying and trying to be nice, just like my wife when she said I&amp;rsquo;m doing a good job&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; and so on, in perpetuity, etcetera.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3">
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m constantly working past the fact that I&amp;rsquo;m a college educated white dude in the U.S. with a white collar job that I really enjoy. I feel like I don&amp;rsquo;t deserve to be depressed, or don&amp;rsquo;t deserve treatment, I already hit so many damn lotteries! This reeks of the same logic as &amp;ldquo;there are starving children in Africa, so you need to finish all your food&amp;rdquo;. No matter what I do with the food on my plate, I ain&amp;rsquo;t solving the more tragic problem. So I need to just eat/not-eat/whatever the fuck is the option that makes sense in this simile.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4">
&lt;p>This eventually led me to get rejected from most colleges I applied to, which again felt like the apocalypse. Ultimately I think this actually worked out for the best, but good luck trying to convince me of that at the time.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:5">
&lt;p>And even if they did, they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t enjoy it or connect with it.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>College is a Scam*</title><link>https://kalverra.github.io/essays/college-is-a-scam/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 19:26:51 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kalverra.github.io/essays/college-is-a-scam/</guid><description>&lt;p>I recently went to see my brother-in-law graduate from college. There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of attitudes present at any graduation event, the pride and accomplishment of so many young people and their parents easily sweeps you into a happy embrace. There&amp;rsquo;s also consequently an underlying sense of surety. The surety that these years of education and a degree signifying that fact were all good ideas. I went through the same process not too long ago and have possessed this same surety for the entirety of my life. So imagine my whiplash as I came across a Twitter tirade of intelligent and highly educated tech leaders claiming that a college degree is one big scam.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet">&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr">College is a scam, you don’t need it.&lt;br>&lt;br>- Stanford ‘00, ‘04, ‘05, ‘06 &lt;a href="https://t.co/VonzG04L0I">https://t.co/VonzG04L0I&lt;/a>&lt;/p>&amp;mdash; Balaji (@balajis) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/balajis/status/1472209100536614914?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December 18, 2021&lt;/a>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8">&lt;/script>
&lt;p>This isn&amp;rsquo;t exactly a new sentiment among tech leaders, but the idea&amp;rsquo;s recent resurgence got me thinking about the worth of a college degree in the modern U.S. Let&amp;rsquo;s break down &lt;a href="https://balajis.com/">Balaji Srinivasan&lt;/a>&amp;rsquo;s statement above.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="scam-is-harsh-but" >&amp;ldquo;Scam&amp;rdquo; is harsh, but&amp;hellip;
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#scam-is-harsh-but">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>You&amp;rsquo;ve probably heard of this thing called student loans that everyone freaks out about. You know, that massive number that fills your dreams with anxiety? The primary contributor to that is tuition, which has been on a meteoric rise for a while now. A 4 year degree from a state school will run you about $35,000 for a 4-year degree, while more elite or private institutions will have you pony up $100k+. The rising cost of school far outpaces any increase in wages.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;img src="https://educationdata.org/wp-content/uploads/78/historical-cost-of-tuition-and-fees.webp" alt="cost of college">
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Not to mention, most of the time that doesn&amp;rsquo;t include things like food, rent, books, that stupid fucking clicker thing that your professor insists you NEED to buy for $60. Not only are you paying for the privilege of doing homework, you also need to keep a whole-ass person alive while doing it. Do you remember your budget in college?&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Category&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Budgeted&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Rent&lt;/td>
&lt;td>$400&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Food&lt;/td>
&lt;td>$100&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Weed&lt;/td>
&lt;td>$100&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Not exactly a glamorous existence.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Adding insult to injury, free access to information has never been more prevalent. Even when I was in college classes, I would often end up learning far more about the subject from online resources than my professors.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;img src="https://i.imgur.com/NbCc7ca.jpeg" alt="Stack Overflow cap">
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If I&amp;rsquo;m paying such high costs for my education, I&amp;rsquo;d expect the quality to be equally high. The people teaching at colleges are certainly impressive, holding PHDs in their fields and generally being incredibly smart people, but I don&amp;rsquo;t need a math PHD to teach me basic calculus. If I was going to pay for a chess coach, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t hire a Grand Master. That level of expertise would cost a requisite amount of money, and at my chess level, the Grand Master wouldn&amp;rsquo;t teach me any better than some 12 year old with a couple trophies. Most colleges seem to agree with me, as they often have grad students teach undergrad courses (a practice I saw no discount on my tuition for). When you&amp;rsquo;re at a basic level, it matters a lot more on how good at &lt;em>teaching&lt;/em> the topic your instructor is, not the instructor&amp;rsquo;s own level of mastery.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The primary justification for the high costs is that a college degree will prepare you for the work force, but college isn&amp;rsquo;t an ideal job-training simulator. I went to college to become a professional programmer, but a significant portion of my time was spent in Philosophy and English classes, subjects that don&amp;rsquo;t come up too often when writing code. Even some of my computer science classes I probably could have done without entirely.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how true this is for other professions, but there&amp;rsquo;s a large disparity between the skills school teaches you and the skills companies need. I&amp;rsquo;d probably become a professional programmer faster if I had focused on problems that companies deal with instead of the problems school taught me with.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="and-you-do-need-it" >And you DO need it
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#and-you-do-need-it">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Here&amp;rsquo;s where the title&amp;rsquo;s asterisk comes in: society still values college. but the primary barrier to entry of your standard white-collar job is that piece of paper with fancy calligraphy on it. How do you plan to be hired as an accountant, engineer, or architect without a degree&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>? If you&amp;rsquo;ve already been in the industry for a while, it&amp;rsquo;s not likely to be a problem. You&amp;rsquo;ve gotten your foot in the door and proven your worth. But if your only credentials are a high school diploma and a list of books you&amp;rsquo;ve been reading in your parents&amp;rsquo; basement the past few years, prepare to be disappointed. There&amp;rsquo;s plenty of complex and well-paying jobs that you can obtain without a college degree; trade jobs like plumbers and electricians immediately come to mind. But if you&amp;rsquo;re a klutz like me, working with your hands is an unlikely prospect.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some professions and organizations are tolerant with hiring self-taught people, but only if you have some other way to prove you know what you&amp;rsquo;re doing. Tech is the biggest example because its barrier to entry is so low and the open-source community makes knowledge widely free and available. If a fresh high school grad came to me with a few projects she could speak passionately about and discuss with me in depth, I&amp;rsquo;d have few issues in hiring her. All she needs to prove her knowledge is a computer and a &lt;a href="https://github.com/">GitHub&lt;/a> portfolio. Most other industries lack the ability to assess candidates like this, and even some tech organizations won&amp;rsquo;t bother.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is not to say this is a fair position for society to take. It&amp;rsquo;s also not implying that the piece of paper, and the requisite acknowledgement of your competence from corporate America, is all that college is good for (we&amp;rsquo;ll get to that later). It&amp;rsquo;s to say that in today&amp;rsquo;s world, there&amp;rsquo;s far cheaper and more effective ways to obtain an education, but corporate America is slow to adapt. So the traditional degree is largely still a requirement, even if it&amp;rsquo;s not the most optimal way to prepare for the workforce.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;img src="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Gates#/media/File:Bill_Gates_2017_%28cropped%29.jpg" alt="William Doors">
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>People always like to point to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Gates">Bill Gates&lt;/a> (or &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Zuckerberg">Zuckerberg&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Dell">Dell&lt;/a>) as a reason to not go to college, it obviously worked out for him. His path is not a consistent one to emulate, and Bill himself encourages people to &lt;a href="https://www.gatesnotes.com/Education/11-Million-College-Grads">not be like him&lt;/a>. These people are the results of exceptional intelligence, motivation, and luck. Lacking any of those three will lead to failure for 99% of people.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="its-not-all-about-the-money" >It&amp;rsquo;s Not All About the Money
&lt;span>
&lt;a href="#its-not-all-about-the-money">
&lt;svg viewBox="0 0 28 23" height="100%" width="19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path d="M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;path d="M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71" fill="none" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-miterlimit="10" stroke-width="2"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>College isn&amp;rsquo;t the most efficient job training simulator because it wasn&amp;rsquo;t designed to be. It&amp;rsquo;s meant to help you grow as a person with broad intellectual achievement. And you get to do so in an environment with tons of other smart, young people looking to learn and have fun. That time I spent in English, Philosophy and Biology classes in college didn&amp;rsquo;t do much of anything for my programming abilities, but that time taught me how to be a more well-rounded human, and how to think critically about the world around me.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>I submit that this is what the real, no bullshit value of your liberal
arts education is supposed to be about: how to keep from going through
your comfortable, prosperous, respectable adult life dead, unconscious, a
slave to your head and to your natural default setting of being uniquely,
completely, imperially alone day in and day out.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ndash; &lt;em>This is Water by David Foster Wallace&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>If your dream is to become a doctor or lawyer, where you&amp;rsquo;re usually legally obligated to have a certain college degree, expect to be laughed out of every interview. If you ever manage to get that far.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item></channel></rss>